<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="info"
  docName="draft-vulnetix-crit-01"
  ipr="trust200902"
  submissionType="independent"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="CRIT">Cloud Resource Identifier Templates (CRIT)</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-vulnetix-crit-01"/>

    <author fullname="CD Langton" initials="CD" surname="Langton">
      <organization>Vulnetix</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>
        <email>chris@vulnetix.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.vulnetix.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2026" month="March" day="27"/>

    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>Independent Submission</workgroup>

    <keyword>cloud security</keyword>
    <keyword>vulnerability</keyword>
    <keyword>CSPM</keyword>
    <keyword>CVE</keyword>
    <keyword>cloud resource identifier</keyword>
    <keyword>exposure window</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document specifies the Cloud Resource Identifier Templates (CRIT) format.
        A CRIT record provides a machine-readable, parameterised template for locating
        cloud-native resources affected by a known vulnerability. CRITs do not define
        cloud resource identifier schemas; those are defined normatively by each cloud
        provider. CRITs define a variable system for expressing partially-known or
        consumer-resolved values within those provider-defined schemas, together with
        temporal, remediation, and detection metadata sufficient to determine exposure
        status and drive remediation workflows.
      </t>
      <t>
        Each CRIT record is bound to exactly one vulnerability identifier.
        Cross-provider and multi-resource-type coverage of a single vulnerability is
        expressed as a set of CRIT records sharing the same vulnerability identifier, each
        independently specifying the provider-specific fix details, propagation
        mechanism, and detection strategy applicable to that resource type.
      </t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="intro">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        This document specifies the Cloud Resource Identifier Templates (CRIT)
        format, a machine-readable schema for describing cloud infrastructure
        resources affected by known vulnerabilities. CRIT provides parameterised
        templates over provider-native identifier schemas, together with fix
        propagation semantics, exposure window computation rules, and detection
        metadata sufficient to drive automated remediation workflows.
      </t>

      <section anchor="overview">
        <name>Overview</name>
        <t>
          <xref target="CPE23">CPE</xref> and <xref target="PURL">PURL</xref>
          model the vulnerable entity as a build-from-source artifact — something
          with a static name, a version string, and a build-time identity that
          persists across deployment. Cloud infrastructure resources do not have
          these properties. An RDS instance, an EKS cluster, and a Cloudflare
          Worker are each identified by provider-native runtime identifiers whose
          components include consumer-specific variables (account identifiers,
          region codes, resource IDs) that do not exist until the resource is
          deployed. No package name, version string, or source repository URL
          applies.
        </t>
        <t>
          CRIT defines a parameterised template system over these provider-native
          identifier schemas, together with fix propagation semantics, exposure
          window computation rules, and detection metadata. It integrates with
          CVEListv5 (<xref target="CVEListv5"/>) ADP containers and OSV schema
          (<xref target="OSV-Schema"/>) using their existing extension mechanisms.
          Risk-based prioritisation signals such as EPSS (<xref target="EPSS"/>)
          remain complementary inputs to consumer tooling.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="problem-statement">
        <name>The Identifier Gap</name>
        <t>
          CPE and PURL both assume the vulnerable entity is produced by a build
          process — compiled from source, packaged into a distributable artifact,
          and deployed by installing that artifact. This assumption holds for
          operating systems, libraries, and application binaries. It does not
          hold for cloud infrastructure resources.
        </t>
        <t>
          A cloud resource is instantiated by a provider API call, not by
          installing a package. It is identified by a provider-native runtime
          identifier — an ARN, an Azure Resource ID, a GCP Resource Name, an
          OCID, or a Cloudflare Locator — that is assigned at creation time and
          contains components specific to the consumer's account, region, and
          deployment. These identifiers have no analogue in any package registry.
          There is no source repository, no version string, and no build
          manifest.
        </t>
        <t>
          Representing a cloud resource as a <tt>pkg:generic/</tt> PURL, a
          synthesised CPE string, or a custom PURL type does not resolve this
          gap. The <xref target="PURL">PURL specification</xref> defines no
          registered type for cloud infrastructure resources. The
          <tt>pkg:cloud/</tt> convention observed in the OSV ecosystem (see
          <xref target="ui-osv-conventions"/>) is not a registered PURL type.
          Regardless of identifier scheme, the resulting string carries none
          of the information required to determine whether a specific deployed
          resource is affected: the deployment date relative to the fix, the
          propagation mechanism, whether the consumer has taken the required
          action, or whether a configuration change has since been reverted.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="exposure-model">
        <name>Cloud Resource Exposure Model</name>
        <t>
          For package vulnerabilities, affected status is determined by a version
          comparison: if the installed version falls within the affected range,
          the package is vulnerable. Cloud resources have no equivalent
          comparison. Affected status is a function of four factors that must be
          evaluated simultaneously:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>When the resource was deployed relative to when the provider fix
          became available.</li>
          <li>The fix propagation type — whether the fix applies automatically,
          requires a version update, requires a configuration change, or
          requires the resource to be destroyed and recreated.</li>
          <li>Whether the consumer has taken the required action, if any.</li>
          <li>Whether a previously applied remediation has been reverted by
          subsequent configuration drift.</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
          No static identifier carries these factors. A CPE or PURL string
          identifies what the resource is; it does not encode how the fix
          reaches the resource or whether a specific instance has been
          remediated. Each consumer tool that evaluates cloud resource exposure
          must independently model these semantics.
        </t>
        <t>
          Discovery additionally requires interpolation. The identifier for a
          specific resource instance contains consumer-specific variables —
          account, region, resource ID — that must be substituted at resolution
          time. A single CRIT template represents all instances of a resource
          type; resolution produces the concrete identifier for a specific
          instance.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="crit-approach">
        <name>CRIT Approach</name>
        <t>
          CRIT addresses the identifier gap by defining a parameterisation layer
          over provider-native identifier schemas. A CRIT record does not invent
          a new identifier format. It parameterises the identifier format the
          provider already defines, expressing consumer-specific and
          context-dependent values as variable slots within the provider's own
          schema.
        </t>
        <t>
          Each CRIT record carries the fix propagation type, shared
          responsibility model, temporal metadata, remediation actions, and
          detection queries required for a consumer to evaluate exposure and
          drive remediation for a specific vulnerability on a specific cloud
          resource type. The record is bound to exactly one vulnerability
          identifier. Cross-provider and multi-resource-type coverage of a
          single vulnerability is expressed as a set of records sharing the same
          vulnerability identifier, each independently specifying the
          provider-specific semantics.
        </t>
        <t>
          CRIT does not replace CVE, CPE, or PURL. It complements them by
          providing the cloud resource scope, fix propagation semantics, and
          exposure window computation that those schemes do not address.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="crit-is-and-is-not">
        <name>What CRIT Is and What It Is Not</name>
        <t>
          If the problem could be described in one word, that word is
          <strong>affected</strong>. For packages, "affected" is a version
          comparison. For cloud, "affected" is a function of four factors
          evaluated simultaneously: when the resource was deployed relative to
          the fix, the fix propagation type, whether the consumer has acted, and
          whether a previously applied remediation has been reverted by
          configuration drift. No static identifier carries these factors. CRIT
          encodes all four.
        </t>

        <section anchor="crit-is">
          <name>CRIT Is</name>
          <ul>
            <li><strong>A template engine for cloud-native resources.</strong>
            Discovery requires interpolation of consumer-specific variables
            (account, region, resource ID) at resolution time. No static
            identifier can express this.</li>

            <li><strong>A solution to the "affected" problem.</strong> It
            encodes deployment timing, fix propagation type, consumer action
            state, and configuration drift status — everything required to
            determine whether a specific deployed resource is impacted.</li>

            <li><strong>A parameterisation layer over provider-native identifier
            schemas.</strong> CRITs do not invent identifier formats. AWS ARNs,
            Azure Resource IDs, GCP Resource Names, Cloudflare Locators, and
            Oracle OCIDs are adopted as-is. CRIT parameterises them with
            variable slots.</li>

            <li><strong>An extension to existing vulnerability data
            formats.</strong> CRIT integrates with CVEListv5 ADP containers and
            OSV schema using their existing extension mechanisms. It does not
            require changes to those specifications.</li>

            <li><strong>A machine-readable encoding of fix propagation,
            remediation actions, detection queries, and exposure window
            computation</strong> — the metadata that turns a vulnerability
            advisory into an actionable remediation workflow for cloud
            resources.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>

        <section anchor="crit-is-not">
          <name>CRIT Is Not</name>
          <ul>
            <li><strong>Not an identifier.</strong> Cloud resources already have
            identifiers. CRITs reference them; they do not define new ones. The
            CRIT vectorString is a natural composite key (replacing the UUID),
            not a resource identifier.</li>

            <li><strong>Not a replacement for CPE, PURL, CycloneDX, or
            SPDX.</strong> Those standards solve identification, inventory, and
            risk prioritisation for build-from-source artifacts. CRIT
            complements them by addressing cloud resource scope where they do
            not apply.</li>

            <li><strong>Not a single string that can encode the full
            record.</strong> The CRIT vectorString is a lossy compact encoding
            of 12 enumerable fields from a 30+ field record. Descriptive
            values, detection queries, remediation action descriptions,
            provider-native templates, and consumer-specific variables cannot be
            represented in any static string. Any attempt to reduce CRIT to a
            single-string identifier discards the metadata that solves the
            problem.</li>

            <li><strong>Not a risk scoring or prioritisation
            system.</strong> CRIT does not assign severity, CVSS scores, or
            risk rankings. Risk-based prioritisation signals (EPSS, CVSS, SSVC)
            remain complementary inputs to consumer tooling.</li>

            <li><strong>Not a replacement for cloud provider security
            advisories.</strong> CRIT references provider advisories; it does
            not replace them. Provider advisory URLs and identifiers are carried
            as metadata within the record.</li>

            <li><strong>Not a software inventory or bill-of-materials
            format.</strong> CRIT records describe how vulnerabilities affect
            cloud resources. They are not an inventory of deployed resources or
            a software composition.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>

        <section anchor="why-not-purl">
          <name>Why Not PURL?</name>
          <t>
            <xref target="PURL">PURL</xref> succeeds because package identity
            is static: <tt>pkg:npm/@angular/core@12.3.1</tt> is the same string
            regardless of where the package is installed. Cloud resource identity
            is not static. An RDS instance's ARN contains an account ID, region,
            and resource ID that do not exist until the resource is deployed.
            Even if a PURL were constructed at that granularity, it would carry
            none of the information required to determine affected status: the
            deployment date relative to the fix, the propagation mechanism,
            whether the consumer has acted, or whether a configuration change
            has been reverted.
          </t>
          <t>
            The <tt>pkg:cloud/</tt> convention observed in the OSV ecosystem
            (see <xref target="ui-osv-conventions"/>) is not a registered PURL
            type. Regardless of the type scheme, a static string cannot express
            the interpolation that discovery requires or the temporal and
            propagation logic that affected-status determination demands.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="conventions">
        <name>Conventions and Terminology</name>

        <section anchor="requirements-language">
          <name>Requirements Language</name>
          <t>
            The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
            "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
            "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
            "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
            "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and
            "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
            described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
            <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all
            capitals, as shown here.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="terminology">
          <name>Terminology</name>
          <t>
            The following terms are used throughout this document.
          </t>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt>CRIT Record:</dt>
            <dd>A JSON object conforming to this specification that describes
            the scope, remediation, and detection characteristics of a single
            vulnerability as it applies to a single cloud resource type.</dd>

            <dt>CRIT Template:</dt>
            <dd>A parameterised string in which variable slots represent
            consumer-specific or context-dependent values. After all slots are
            resolved, the result is a valid provider-native resource
            identifier.</dd>

            <dt>CRIT Dictionary:</dt>
            <dd>A machine-readable catalogue enumerating valid (provider,
            service, resource_type) tuples with their corresponding templates
            and metadata. See <xref target="dictionary"/>.</dd>

            <dt>CRIT Vector String:</dt>
            <dd>A compact, deterministic, human-readable encoding of a CRIT
            record's classification and identity fields, modelled on CVSS
            vector strings. See <xref target="crit-vector-string"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Natural Key:</dt>
            <dd>The tuple (vuln_id, provider, service, resource_type) that
            uniquely identifies a CRIT record within a conformant corpus.</dd>

            <dt>Producer:</dt>
            <dd>An entity that creates and emits CRIT records.</dd>

            <dt>Consumer:</dt>
            <dd>An entity that processes CRIT records to evaluate cloud
            resource exposure, deploy detections, or drive remediation
            workflows.</dd>

            <dt>Conformant Corpus:</dt>
            <dd>A collection of CRIT records in which no two records share the
            same natural key.</dd>

            <dt>Provider:</dt>
            <dd>A cloud service vendor whose resources are covered by this
            specification.  Supported values are: <tt>aws</tt>,
            <tt>azure</tt>, <tt>gcp</tt>, <tt>cloudflare</tt>,
            <tt>oracle</tt>, <tt>salesforce</tt>, <tt>sap</tt>, and
            <tt>servicenow</tt>.  Each provider maintains its own resource
            identification scheme; CRIT encodes those schemes as templates
            without altering or extending them.</dd>

            <dt>Service:</dt>
            <dd>A distinct offering within a provider's portfolio, identified
            by a lowercase underscore-delimited key (e.g., <tt>ec2</tt>,
            <tt>kubernetes_engine</tt>, <tt>waf</tt>).</dd>

            <dt>Resource Type:</dt>
            <dd>A specific kind of resource within a service, identified by a
            key matching the provider's API conventions (e.g., <tt>instance</tt>,
            <tt>cluster</tt>, <tt>waf_ruleset</tt>).</dd>

            <dt>Template Format:</dt>
            <dd>The provider-native identifier schema used by a template:
            <tt>aws_arn</tt>, <tt>azure_resource_id</tt>,
            <tt>gcp_resource_name</tt>, <tt>cloudflare_locator</tt>, or
            <tt>oracle_ocid</tt>.</dd>

            <dt>Variable Slot:</dt>
            <dd>A delimited placeholder within a CRIT template, enclosed in
            braces, that represents a value to be supplied or fixed.</dd>

            <dt>Named Variable:</dt>
            <dd>A slot whose value the consumer must supply at resolution time.
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name}</tt>.</dd>

            <dt>Wildcard:</dt>
            <dd>A slot representing any value, used for inventory enumeration.
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name=*}</tt>.</dd>

            <dt>Hardcoded:</dt>
            <dd>A slot with a fixed value determined by the provider schema.
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name=value}</tt>.</dd>

            <dt>Empty:</dt>
            <dd>A slot for a field that is structurally present but
            semantically inapplicable to the resource type. Syntax:
            <tt>{field-name=}</tt>.</dd>

            <dt>Slot Resolution:</dt>
            <dd>The process of substituting concrete values into variable
            slots to produce a live provider identifier.</dd>

            <dt>Resource Lifecycle:</dt>
            <dd>A classification of a resource type's operational behaviour
            with respect to data durability and replacement. See
            <xref target="schema-lifecycle"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Shared Responsibility:</dt>
            <dd>The remediation responsibility model describing whether the
            provider, the consumer, or both must act to remediate a
            vulnerability. See <xref target="schema-shared-resp"/>.</dd>

            <dt>VEX Status:</dt>
            <dd>The Vulnerability Exploitability eXchange status of a record:
            affected, fixed, not_affected, or under_investigation. Aligns with
            the OpenVEX (<xref target="OpenVEX"/>) and CSAF VEX
            (<xref target="CSAF-VEX"/>) vocabularies. See
            <xref target="schema-vex"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Fix Propagation:</dt>
            <dd>The mechanism by which a provider-released fix reaches
            existing deployed resources. See
            <xref target="schema-propagation"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Exposure Window:</dt>
            <dd>The time interval [W_start, W_end] during which a specific
            resource instance is vulnerable. See
            <xref target="exposure-window"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Existing Deployments Remain Vulnerable:</dt>
            <dd>A boolean indicating whether resources deployed before the
            provider fix date remain in the exposure window absent explicit
            consumer action.</dd>

            <dt>Remediation Action:</dt>
            <dd>An ordered step a consumer takes to remediate or mitigate a
            vulnerability on a specific resource type. See
            <xref target="schema-remediation-actions"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Compensating Control:</dt>
            <dd>A remediation action that reduces exploitability but does not
            fully remediate the vulnerability.</dd>

            <dt>Detection Entry:</dt>
            <dd>A log query, metric filter, or alerting rule for identifying
            vulnerable configurations, active exploitation, or configuration
            drift. See <xref target="schema-detections"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Detection Phase:</dt>
            <dd>The lifecycle stage of a detection: pre_fix, exploitation,
            post_fix, or misconfiguration. See
            <xref target="detection-phase"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Pending Reason:</dt>
            <dd>An enumerated value indicating why a detection entry is a
            placeholder without a functional query. See
            <xref target="detection-pending"/>.</dd>

            <dt>Vulnerability Identifier:</dt>
            <dd>A string uniquely identifying the vulnerability a CRIT record
            relates to (e.g., CVE-2024-6387).</dd>

            <dt>Provider Fix Date:</dt>
            <dd>The date a provider made a fix generally available.</dd>

            <dt>Vulnerability Published Date:</dt>
            <dd>The date the vulnerability was publicly disclosed.</dd>

            <dt>Service Available Date:</dt>
            <dd>The date a provider's service became generally available,
            bounding the earliest possible deployment of affected
            resources.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>

      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="scope">
      <name>Scope and Relationship to Provider Schemas</name>
      <t>
        CRITs operate as a parameterisation layer over externally-defined resource
        identifier schemas. The authoritative definition of each identifier format is
        owned by its respective provider:
      </t>
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr><th>Provider</th><th>Identifier Type</th><th>Normative Reference</th></tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr><td>AWS</td><td>Amazon Resource Name (ARN)</td><td><xref target="AWS-ARN"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>Azure</td><td>Azure Resource ID</td><td><xref target="Azure-ResourceID"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>GCP</td><td>GCP Resource Name</td><td><xref target="GCP-ResourceName"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>Cloudflare</td><td>Cloudflare API Locator</td><td><xref target="CF-API"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>Oracle</td><td>Oracle Cloud ID (OCID)</td><td><xref target="OCI-OCID"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>Salesforce</td><td>REST API Resource URL</td><td><xref target="SF-REST-API"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>SAP BTP</td><td>BTP / OData / SuccessFactors URL</td><td><xref target="SAP-BTP"/></td></tr>
          <tr><td>ServiceNow</td><td>Table API URL</td><td><xref target="SN-TABLE-API"/></td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        This specification does not alter, extend, or redefine any provider identifier
        schema. A conformant CRIT template <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> produce a string that,
        after variable resolution, is a valid identifier according to the applicable
        provider schema.
      </t>
      <t>
        A CRIT template <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> use <tt>pkg:generic/</tt> or any PURL
        type that implies a build-from-source artifact to represent a cloud
        infrastructure resource. Such usage introduces ambiguous semantics in tooling
        designed around the build-artifact assumption and is explicitly out of scope for
        this specification.
      </t>
      <t>This specification does not cover:</t>
      <ul>
        <li>How CRIT records are extracted from vulnerability data sources.</li>
        <li>Internal database schemas or persistence mechanisms.</li>
        <li>Vulnerability ingestion pipelines or NLP-based service detection.</li>
        <li>Source corpus processing.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="variable-system">
      <name>The CRIT Variable System</name>

      <section anchor="vs-overview">
        <name>Overview</name>
        <t>
          A CRIT record is a template engine for cloud-native resources: discovery
          requires interpolation of consumer-specific variables at resolution time,
          which no static identifier can express.
        </t>
        <t>
          A CRIT template string is a provider identifier format with zero or more
          variable slots. Each slot expresses one of four states. The choice of state
          is normative: it is determined by the semantics of the field for the given
          resource type, not by what the consumer happens to know.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="vs-syntax">
        <name>Slot Syntax</name>
        <t>
          Variable slots are delimited with <tt>{</tt> and <tt>}</tt>. The content
          within the delimiters is a slot descriptor with the following ABNF (<xref target="RFC5234"/>) grammar:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>Slot ABNF Grammar</name>
          <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
slot            = "{" slot-descriptor "}"
slot-descriptor = named-var / wildcard / empty-marker / hardcoded
named-var       = field-name
wildcard        = field-name "=" "*"
empty-marker    = field-name "="
hardcoded       = field-name "=" literal-value
field-name      = 1*( ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" )
literal-value   = 1*( ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" / "." / ":" )
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The characters <tt>{</tt> and <tt>}</tt> are reserved as slot delimiters and
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> appear in <tt>literal-value</tt> or as literal
          characters within a template string outside of slot expressions.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="vs-design">
        <name>Design Relationship to RFC 6570</name>
        <t>
          CRIT slot syntax uses curly-brace delimiters that resemble
          <xref target="RFC6570"/> URI Templates. This resemblance is
          intentional but superficial. CRIT slots are <strong>not</strong>
          URI Templates and implementations <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> process
          them with an RFC 6570 expansion engine.
        </t>
        <t>
          The CRIT variable system defines exactly four slot states. The
          number four is a design invariant: each additional state
          multiplies the number of producer-consumer interactions that
          require specification and testing. Because cloud provider
          identifier schemas are not standardised, and the number of
          providers is unbounded, the slot state vocabulary must remain
          fixed to prevent combinatorial growth in conformance surface
          area. The four states are the minimum set that satisfies all
          operational requirements defined in this specification:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li><strong>Named variable</strong> (<tt>{field}</tt>):
          Consumer-supplied value. This is the only state that
          corresponds to <xref target="RFC6570"/> Level 1 simple string
          expansion.</li>
          <li><strong>Wildcard</strong> (<tt>{field=*}</tt>): Population
          enumeration. No <xref target="RFC6570"/> equivalent exists.
          The semantic is an inventory operation, not a URI
          construction.</li>
          <li><strong>Empty</strong> (<tt>{field=}</tt>): Structurally
          present but inapplicable. The resolved value is the empty
          string. <xref target="RFC6570"/> does not distinguish between
          an undefined variable and a field that is normatively absent
          from the provider schema; CRIT requires this distinction to
          prevent consumers from treating a structurally absent field as
          an unknown value requiring resolution.</li>
          <li><strong>Hardcoded</strong> (<tt>{field=literal}</tt>):
          Provider-fixed value. The value is determined by the provider
          schema, not by the consumer. This state is required because
          some provider identifier schemas contain positional fields
          whose value is invariant for a given resource type (e.g., a
          region field that is always <tt>us-east-1</tt> for a global
          service). Without a distinct hardcoded state, a consumer
          cannot distinguish a provider-fixed value from a
          consumer-specific value that coincidentally matches.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          <xref target="RFC6570"/> operators (<tt>+</tt>, <tt>#</tt>,
          <tt>.</tt>, <tt>/</tt>, <tt>;</tt>, <tt>?</tt>,
          <tt>&amp;</tt>) are not supported. CRIT templates use simple
          string replacement only. A fully-resolved CRIT template — one
          in which every named-variable slot has been substituted with a
          concrete value, every empty slot resolved to the empty string,
          and every hardcoded slot resolved to its literal — produces a
          valid provider-native resource identifier. The result is a
          plain string, not a URI Template expansion.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="vs-states">
        <name>The Four Slot States</name>

        <section anchor="vs-named">
          <name>Named Variable</name>
          <t>
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name}</tt>
          </t>
          <t>
            The slot represents a value the consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> supply at
            resolution time. A consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> treat a named variable
            as implying any default value. A consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> substitute a
            concrete value before using the template as a live identifier.
          </t>
          <t>
            Examples: <tt>{region}</tt>, <tt>{account}</tt>, <tt>{resource-id}</tt>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="vs-wildcard">
          <name>Wildcard</name>
          <t>
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name=*}</tt>
          </t>
          <t>
            The slot represents "any value" and is used for inventory matching across a
            population of resources. A wildcard <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used as a
            live identifier against a provider API; it is a query pattern only. A
            consumer <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> expand a wildcard by enumerating known values
            from their inventory. A consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> record when a wildcard
            remains unexpanded, as an unexpanded wildcard indicates incomplete inventory
            coverage.
          </t>
          <t>
            Examples: <tt>{region=*}</tt> matches all regions; <tt>{account=*}</tt>
            matches all accounts.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="vs-empty">
          <name>Empty</name>
          <t>
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name=}</tt>
          </t>
          <t>
            The slot represents a field that is structurally present in the provider
            schema but not applicable for this resource type. The resolved value is the
            empty string. This <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be confused with an unknown
            value (use named variable) or a match-all (use wildcard). It is a precise
            semantic statement that the field does not apply to this resource type.
          </t>
          <t>
            Example: GCP global resources carry no zone; the zone slot is expressed as
            <tt>{zone=}</tt>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="vs-hardcoded">
          <name>Hardcoded</name>
          <t>
            Syntax: <tt>{field-name=literal-value}</tt>
          </t>
          <t>
            The slot represents a fixed value determined by the provider schema for this
            resource type. A CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use hardcoded state only
            for values normatively fixed by the provider schema. A consumer
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the hardcoded value as-is and <bcp14>MUST
            NOT</bcp14> substitute an alternative value.
          </t>
          <t>
            Example: <tt>{region=us-east-1}</tt> for AWS IAM resources, which the AWS
            ARN schema requires to always be <tt>us-east-1</tt>.
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="vs-selection">
        <name>Slot State Selection Rules</name>
        <t>
          A CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> select the slot state according to the
          following precedence:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>If the provider schema normatively fixes this field to a specific value
          for the resource type: <strong>hardcoded</strong>.</li>
          <li>If the provider schema specifies the field is structurally absent or
          inapplicable for this resource type: <strong>empty</strong>.</li>
          <li>If the field represents a cross-resource population query rather than a
          specific resource: <strong>wildcard</strong>.</li>
          <li>Otherwise: <strong>named variable</strong>.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          A CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> use wildcard as a fallback when the
          correct state is unknown. An unknown consumer-specific value is always a named
          variable; wildcard is a deliberate semantic choice meaning "enumerate all".
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="schema">
      <name>CRIT Record Schema</name>
      <t>
        All field names are lowercase snake_case. The schema is expressed in JSON.
        Unless stated otherwise, absent optional fields are interpreted as null. All
        date values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be expressed in ISO&nbsp;8601 <xref target="ISO8601"/> full-date format
        (<tt>YYYY-MM-DD</tt>) in UTC. Time-of-day components <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
        omitted unless a provider advisory specifies intraday precision is meaningful.
      </t>

      <section anchor="schema-envelope">
        <name>Envelope and Identity</name>
        <figure>
          <name>Envelope Fields</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "vectorString": "<crit-vector>",
  "vuln_id": "<string>",
  "provider": "<enum>",
  "service": "<string>",
  "resource_type": "<string>",
  "resource_lifecycle": "<enum>",
  "shared_responsibility": "<enum>",
  "vex_status": "<enum>"
}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Field</th><th>Required</th><th>Type</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>vectorString</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>string</td><td>Canonical CRIT vector string computed from record fields. See <xref target="crit-vector-string"/>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>vuln_id</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>string</td><td>The vulnerability this record relates to. <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match exactly one vulnerability per record.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>provider</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>enum</td><td>One of: <tt>aws</tt>, <tt>azure</tt>, <tt>gcp</tt>, <tt>cloudflare</tt>, <tt>oracle</tt>, <tt>salesforce</tt>, <tt>sap</tt>, <tt>servicenow</tt>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>service</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>string</td><td>Provider service key (e.g., <tt>lambda</tt>, <tt>aks</tt>, <tt>cloud_sql</tt>).</td></tr>
            <tr><td>resource_type</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>string</td><td>Specific resource type within the service (e.g., <tt>function</tt>, <tt>cluster</tt>, <tt>instance</tt>).</td></tr>
            <tr><td>resource_lifecycle</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>enum</td><td>See <xref target="schema-lifecycle"/>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>shared_responsibility</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>enum</td><td>See <xref target="schema-shared-resp"/>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>vex_status</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>enum</td><td>See <xref target="schema-vex"/>.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <section anchor="schema-naturalkey">
          <name>Natural Key and Uniqueness</name>
          <t>
            The tuple <tt>(vuln_id, provider, service, resource_type)</tt> constitutes
            the natural key of a CRIT record. Within a conformant corpus, no two records
            <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> share the same natural key. A producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
            enforce this uniqueness constraint before emitting records.
          </t>
          <t>
            When a single vulnerability affects multiple resource types within the same service,
            or the same resource type across multiple providers, the correct
            representation is multiple CRIT records each with a distinct natural key and
            independently specified fix version, propagation mechanism, and detection
            entries. The <tt>vuln_id</tt> field is the join key allowing a consumer to
            retrieve the complete set of records for a given vulnerability.
          </t>
          <t>
            Example: a Kubernetes vulnerability affecting EKS, AKS, and GKE yields three records:
          </t>
          <ul>
            <li><tt>(CVE-2024-XXXX, aws, eks, cluster)</tt></li>
            <li><tt>(CVE-2024-XXXX, azure, aks, cluster)</tt></li>
            <li><tt>(CVE-2024-XXXX, gcp, gke, cluster)</tt></li>
          </ul>
          <t>
            The natural key components are embedded in the CRIT vector string:
            <tt>provider</tt> as the CP metric and <tt>vuln_id</tt>,
            <tt>service</tt>, <tt>resource_type</tt> as the three positional
            qualifiers. The <tt>vectorString</tt> is therefore a canonical
            single-string encoding of the record's natural key combined with
            its classification state.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="crit-vector-string">
          <name>CRIT Vector String</name>
          <t>
            The CRIT vector string is a compact, deterministic, human-readable
            encoding of a record's classification and identity fields. Its
            format is modelled on CVSS vector strings: a versioned prefix
            followed by slash-delimited metric-value pairs and a qualifier
            section.
          </t>

          <t>The ABNF (<xref target="RFC5234"/>) grammar is:</t>
          <sourcecode type="abnf"><![CDATA[
crit-vector     = prefix "/" metrics "#" qualifiers
prefix          = "CRITv" semver
semver          = 1*DIGIT "." 1*DIGIT "." 1*DIGIT
                  [ "-" 1*(ALPHA / DIGIT / ".") ]
metrics         = metric *("/" metric)
metric          = metric-key ":" metric-value
metric-key      = 2ALPHA
metric-value    = 1*(ALPHA / DIGIT)
qualifiers      = qual-value ":" qual-value ":" qual-value
qual-value      = 1*(ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "_" / ".")
          ]]></sourcecode>

          <t>Example:</t>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
CRITv0.2.0/CP:AW/VS:FX/FP:RR/SR:CA/RL:SC/EV:T/PP:1719792000/SA:1514764800#CVE-2024-6387:ec2:instance
          ]]></sourcecode>

          <section anchor="vs-metrics">
            <name>Registered Metrics</name>
            <t>
              A conformant CRIT vector string <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include all
              registered metrics listed below. Registered metrics
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> appear in the canonical order defined by this
              section. A producer <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> append additional
              metrics after the registered set and before the <tt>#</tt>
              delimiter; a consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore unknown metric
              keys without error.
            </t>

            <t><strong>Table 1: Cloud Provider (CP)</strong></t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Value</th><th>Code</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>aws</td><td>AW</td><td>Amazon Web Services</td></tr>
                <tr><td>azure</td><td>MA</td><td>Microsoft Azure</td></tr>
                <tr><td>gcp</td><td>GC</td><td>Google Cloud Platform</td></tr>
                <tr><td>cloudflare</td><td>CF</td><td>Cloudflare</td></tr>
                <tr><td>oracle</td><td>OC</td><td>Oracle Cloud Infrastructure</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

            <t><strong>Table 2: VEX Status (VS)</strong></t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Value</th><th>Code</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>affected</td><td>AF</td><td>Resource type is affected; no fix available or not applied.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>fixed</td><td>FX</td><td>Provider fix is available; provider_fix_date is set.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>not_affected</td><td>NA</td><td>Resource type is not affected or vulnerability is not reachable.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>under_investigation</td><td>UI</td><td>Provider has acknowledged but not confirmed status.</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

            <t><strong>Table 3: Fix Propagation (FP)</strong></t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Value</th><th>Code</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>automatic</td><td>AU</td><td>Provider applies fix transparently.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>config_change</td><td>CC</td><td>Configuration change on existing resource.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>opt_in</td><td>OI</td><td>Fix available but applies to non-default option.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>version_update</td><td>VU</td><td>Consumer must update pinned version or runtime.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>redeploy</td><td>RD</td><td>Consumer must redeploy using existing configuration.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>rebuild_and_redeploy</td><td>RR</td><td>Consumer must rebuild artifact with updated base.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>destroy_recreate</td><td>DC</td><td>Resource must be destroyed and recreated.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>rolling_replace</td><td>RL</td><td>Fleet replacement with coexistence during transition.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>no_fix_available</td><td>NF</td><td>No vendor fix has been released.</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

            <t><strong>Table 4: Shared Responsibility (SR)</strong></t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Value</th><th>Code</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>provider_only</td><td>PO</td><td>Provider is solely responsible for remediation.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>customer_action_required</td><td>CA</td><td>Provider fix exists but customer action is needed.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>customer_only</td><td>CO</td><td>Customer is solely responsible.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>shared</td><td>SH</td><td>Remediation requires coordinated provider and customer action.</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

            <t><strong>Table 5: Resource Lifecycle (RL)</strong></t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Value</th><th>Code</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>ephemeral</td><td>EP</td><td>Short-lived; replaced rather than patched.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>stateful_managed</td><td>SM</td><td>Long-lived; provider manages OS and runtime.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>stateful_customer</td><td>SC</td><td>Long-lived; customer manages OS and runtime.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>config_only</td><td>CF</td><td>No runtime; configuration-only resource.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>global_control_plane</td><td>GC</td><td>Shared control-plane infrastructure.</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

            <t><strong>Table 6: Existing Deployments Remain Vulnerable (EV)</strong></t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Value</th><th>Code</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>true</td><td>T</td><td>Resources deployed before the fix remain vulnerable.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>false</td><td>F</td><td>Provider fix applies retroactively to existing resources.</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>

            <t><strong>Table 7: Vulnerability Published Date (PP)</strong></t>
            <t>
              Unix epoch timestamp (integer seconds). <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>.
              The date the vulnerability was publicly disclosed. Corresponds to
              <tt>temporal.vuln_published_date</tt> converted to epoch seconds.
            </t>

            <t><strong>Table 8: Service Available Date (SA)</strong></t>
            <t>
              Unix epoch timestamp (integer seconds). <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>.
              The date the cloud service became generally available. Corresponds
              to <tt>temporal.service_available_date</tt> converted to epoch
              seconds.
            </t>
          </section>

          <section anchor="vs-qualifiers">
            <name>Qualifiers</name>
            <t>
              Qualifiers appear after the <tt>#</tt> delimiter as positional
              colon-separated values with no metric keys. All three qualifiers
              are <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14> and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> appear in the
              following fixed order:
            </t>
            <table>
              <thead><tr><th>Position</th><th>Field</th><th>Description</th></tr></thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr><td>1</td><td>vuln_id</td><td>Vulnerability identifier (e.g., CVE-2024-6387).</td></tr>
                <tr><td>2</td><td>service</td><td>Provider service key.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>3</td><td>resource_type</td><td>Provider resource type key.</td></tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </section>

          <section anchor="vs-computation">
            <name>Computation and Validation</name>
            <t>A conformant CRIT producer:</t>
            <ul>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> compute <tt>vectorString</tt> from the record's own fields.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include all registered metrics in canonical order (CP, VS, FP, SR, RL, EV, PP, SA).</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the CRIT specification version the record conforms to as the semver prefix.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use only registered abbreviation codes from the tables in <xref target="vs-metrics"/>.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure qualifier values match the corresponding record field values exactly.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MAY</bcp14> append additional metrics after the registered set and before the <tt>#</tt> delimiter.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>A conformant CRIT consumer:</t>
            <ul>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate all known metric keys and their values.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ignore unknown metric keys without error.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject a <tt>vectorString</tt> missing any registered metric.</li>
              <li><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject a <tt>vectorString</tt> where registered metrics appear out of canonical order.</li>
              <li><bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> emit a warning when encountering unknown metric keys.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>

          <section anchor="vs-information-scope">
            <name>Information Scope</name>
            <t>
              The CRIT vector string is a lossy encoding. It carries 12 fields
              from the full CRIT record; the remaining fields are not
              representable in the vector and are discarded during conversion.
            </t>
            <t>Fields carried in the vector string:</t>
            <ul>
              <li>CRIT specification version (prefix).</li>
              <li>Six enumerated classification fields: provider (CP),
              vex_status (VS), fix_propagation (FP), shared_responsibility (SR),
              resource_lifecycle (RL), existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable
              (EV).</li>
              <li>Two required temporal dates as epoch timestamps:
              vuln_published_date (PP), service_available_date (SA).</li>
              <li>Three identity qualifiers: vuln_id, service,
              resource_type.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>Fields not carried in the vector string:</t>
            <ul>
              <li><tt>template</tt> and <tt>template_format</tt> — recoverable
              via dictionary lookup from the <tt>(provider, service,
              resource_type)</tt> tuple embedded in the vector qualifiers and CP
              metric.</li>
              <li>Optional temporal dates: <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date</tt>,
              <tt>provider_acknowledged_date</tt>,
              <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>,
              <tt>customer_deadline_date</tt>, and related fields. A producer
              <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> include these as additional metrics appended
              after the registered set.</li>
              <li>Fix version details: <tt>version_type</tt>,
              <tt>comparison</tt>, <tt>version</tt>, <tt>build_date</tt>,
              <tt>auto_upgrade</tt>, <tt>note</tt>.</li>
              <li>Remediation actions: the complete
              <tt>remediation_actions</tt> array including step-by-step
              instructions, downtime estimates, and compensating control
              flags.</li>
              <li>Detection entries: the complete <tt>detections</tt> array
              including detection queries, query languages, detection phases,
              and pending reasons.</li>
              <li>Advisory metadata: <tt>advisory_id</tt>,
              <tt>advisory_url</tt>.</li>
              <li>Any producer-appended additional metrics beyond the registered
              set are also not preserved when converting from a full JSON record
              to a vector string, unless the converter explicitly retains
              them.</li>
            </ul>
            <t>
              A consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> treat a <tt>vectorString</tt>
              as a complete record representation. A consumer
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the full JSON record for operational
              decisions that require fields not carried in the vector, including
              but not limited to: deploying detection queries, executing
              remediation actions, evaluating fix version comparisons, and
              computing exposure windows.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-template">
        <name>Resource Template</name>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Field</th><th>Required</th><th>Type</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>template</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>string</td><td>Parameterised identifier string. After all named variables are substituted, the result <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid provider identifier for the declared <tt>template_format</tt>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>template_format</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>enum</td><td>One of: <tt>aws_arn</tt>, <tt>azure_resource_id</tt>, <tt>gcp_resource_name</tt>, <tt>cloudflare_locator</tt>, <tt>oracle_ocid</tt>, <tt>salesforce_url</tt>, <tt>sap_btp_url</tt>, <tt>sap_odata_url</tt>, <tt>sap_sf_url</tt>, <tt>servicenow_table_url</tt>.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-temporal">
        <name>Temporal Fields and Exposure Window</name>
        <t>
          These fields collectively define the bounds of exposure. No single field closes
          the exposure window for a given consumer resource; see
          <xref target="exposure-window"/> for the formal computation.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>Temporal Object</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "temporal": {
    "service_available_date": "<date>",
    "vulnerability_introduced_date": "<date>",
    "vulnerability_introduced_date_estimated": "<boolean>",
    "vuln_published_date": "<date>",
    "provider_acknowledged_date": "<date>",
    "provider_fix_date": "<date>",
    "customer_deadline_date": "<date>",
    "customer_deadline_source": "<enum>"
  }
}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt><tt>service_available_date</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>When the provider first made this service or feature generally
          available. Bounds the earliest any resource could have been deployed
          into a vulnerable configuration.</dd>
          <dt><tt>vulnerability_introduced_date</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>When the vulnerability was first present. <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
          predate <tt>vuln_published_date</tt> by months or years. When present,
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be used as W_start of the exposure window.</dd>
          <dt><tt>vulnerability_introduced_date_estimated</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>When <tt>true</tt>, <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date</tt> is an
          estimate. Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> surface this flag in
          exposure window reporting.</dd>
          <dt><tt>vuln_published_date</tt> (REQUIRED):</dt>
          <dd>Date the vulnerability record was first published. <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          match the vulnerability record's <tt>datePublished</tt> field.</dd>
          <dt><tt>provider_acknowledged_date</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>When the provider first confirmed the vulnerability.</dd>
          <dt><tt>provider_fix_date</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>When the provider made a fix generally available.
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be interpreted as the date a consumer
          resource is remediated. Absent when no fix has been released.</dd>
          <dt><tt>customer_deadline_date</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>A normative remediation deadline. Conformant consumer tools
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> use this for SLA computations.</dd>
          <dt><tt>customer_deadline_source</tt> (OPTIONAL):</dt>
          <dd>One of: <tt>cisa_kev</tt>, <tt>pci_dss</tt>, <tt>hipaa</tt>,
          <tt>sox</tt>, <tt>internal_policy</tt>, <tt>other</tt>.
          <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14> when <tt>customer_deadline_date</tt>
          is present.</dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-fix-propagation">
        <name>Fix Propagation and Remediation Actions</name>

        <section anchor="schema-lifecycle">
          <name>Resource Lifecycle</name>
          <t>
            The <tt>resource_lifecycle</tt> field characterises the operational behaviour
            of the resource type with respect to data durability and replacement. This is
            a property of the resource type, not of any specific consumer deployment.
          </t>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>ephemeral</td><td>No durable state; can be replaced without data concern. Examples: Lambda functions, containers, serverless workers.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>stateful_managed</td><td>Provider manages data durability but replacement is disruptive. Examples: RDS, ElastiCache, Cosmos DB, Cloud SQL.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>stateful_customer</td><td>Customer owns data migration entirely. Examples: EBS-backed EC2, self-managed databases on compute.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>config_only</td><td>Pure configuration with no application data. Examples: IAM roles, security groups, WAF rules, DNS records.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>global_control_plane</td><td>Globally scoped; changes propagate with eventual consistency. Examples: CloudFront, Route53, GCP global forwarding rules.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="schema-shared-resp">
          <name>Shared Responsibility</name>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>provider_only</td><td>Provider remediates transparently. The exposure window closes automatically at <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> for all resources.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>customer_action_required</td><td>A fix is available but the consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> take explicit action. <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> does not close the window for existing resources.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>customer_only</td><td>Misconfiguration or insecure default. No provider fix involved. No <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>shared</td><td>Both provider and consumer action are required.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="schema-propagation">
          <name>Fix Propagation</name>
          <t>
            For package vulnerabilities, remediation status is largely derivable from a
            version comparison: if the installed version is at or above the fixed
            version, the package is remediated. Cloud resources have no equivalent.
            There is no installed version to query. A fix becoming available at the
            provider level does not mean any running resource is remediated. Whether a
            specific resource is exposed depends on when it was deployed, what action
            the consumer has taken since, and how the fix propagates to existing
            resources.
          </t>
          <t>
            Some fixes apply automatically to all existing resources regardless of
            deployment date. Most do not. A resource deployed before the fix date under
            a <tt>rebuild_and_redeploy</tt> propagation type is still fully exposed the
            day after <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>. A resource of the same type deployed
            the day after is clean. The two resources are indistinguishable by version
            string -- because neither has one.
          </t>
          <t>
            <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> makes this distinction
            normative and machine-readable. It cannot be derived from a version
            comparison.
          </t>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt><tt>fix_propagation</tt> (REQUIRED):</dt>
            <dd>The mechanism by which the fix reaches existing deployed
            resources. See values below.</dd>
            <dt><tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> (REQUIRED):</dt>
            <dd>When <tt>true</tt>, resources deployed before
            <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> remain in the exposure window unless
            an explicit consumer action has been taken. <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
            be <tt>false</tt> only when <tt>fix_propagation</tt> is
            <tt>automatic</tt> AND <tt>shared_responsibility</tt> is
            <tt>provider_only</tt>.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>Fix propagation enum values:</t>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th><th>Typical Consumer Action</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>automatic</td><td>Provider applies the fix transparently to all existing resources.</td><td>Verify fix is active; no operational change required.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>config_change</td><td>A configuration change on the existing resource is sufficient.</td><td>Apply the change via API, console, or IaC.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>opt_in</td><td>A fix exists but applies to a non-default option.</td><td>Enable the option; update IaC defaults.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>version_update</td><td>Update a pinned version, runtime, or dependency reference.</td><td>Update version reference; trigger redeployment if required.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>redeploy</td><td>Redeploy using the existing configuration.</td><td>Trigger redeployment.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>rebuild_and_redeploy</td><td>Rebuild the artifact with updated base or patched dependencies, then redeploy.</td><td>Update base image, rebuild, push, redeploy.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>destroy_recreate</td><td>The resource <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be destroyed and recreated. In-place upgrade not supported.</td><td>Back up state if applicable, destroy, recreate at fixed version.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>rolling_replace</td><td>Fleet or cluster replacement; old and new instances coexist during transition.</td><td>Trigger rolling update; monitor fleet until 100% replacement.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>no_fix_available</td><td>Provider has not released a fix. <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be absent.</td><td>Apply compensating controls; monitor advisory.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="schema-remediation-actions">
          <name>Remediation Actions</name>
          <t>
            <tt>remediation_actions</tt> is an ordered array. The first entry is the
            primary recommended path. A consumer tool <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> present
            actions in declared sequence order.
          </t>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Field</th><th>Required</th><th>Description</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>sequence</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>1-based ordering index. <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be unique and contiguous within the array starting at 1.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>type</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>One of the <tt>fix_propagation</tt> enum values.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>title</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Short imperative description suitable for a task or ticket title.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>description</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Step-by-step instructions sufficient for an engineer to execute without additional research. <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> include CLI invocations or IaC equivalents where applicable.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>provider_guidance_url</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>Direct link to the provider's advisory or remediation documentation.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>auto_remediable</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Whether a conformant consumer tool <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> automate this action without human approval.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>requires_downtime</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Whether this action causes a service interruption.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>stateful_impact</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>One of: <tt>none</tt>, <tt>backup_recommended</tt>, <tt>backup_restore_required</tt>, <tt>data_migration_required</tt>.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>estimated_downtime_range_seconds</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>Object with <tt>min</tt> and <tt>max</tt> integer bounds. <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14> when <tt>requires_downtime</tt> is <tt>true</tt>. Informative only.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>compensating_control</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>When <tt>true</tt>, this action reduces exploitability but does not fully remediate. A record with only compensating actions <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have <tt>vex_status</tt> of <tt>affected</tt>, not <tt>fixed</tt>.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-fix-version">
        <name>Provider Fix Version</name>
        <t>
          Cloud resources do not use package-style versioning. There is no semver
          string to compare against a fixed bound, no registry entry to look up, and no
          universal version format that applies across providers or even across services
          within a single provider. "Version" for a cloud resource might mean an engine
          release string, a runtime build date, a Kubernetes minor version within a
          release channel, a container image digest, or a platform image creation date
          -- depending on the service. In some cases, such as Cloudflare Workers, there
          is no consumer-visible version at all; only a platform build date.
        </t>
        <t>
          The <tt>provider_fix_version</tt> field is a discriminated object whose
          structure is determined by the <tt>version_type</tt> discriminator. Each
          <tt>version_type</tt> value defines a specific set of fields and a
          <tt>comparison</tt> operator that together give a consumer everything needed
          to evaluate whether a deployed resource meets the fix threshold.
        </t>

        <section anchor="fv-envelope">
          <name>Envelope</name>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Field</th><th>Required</th><th>Description</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>version_type</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Discriminator. Determines which additional fields are present. See Sections <xref target="fv-aws"/> through <xref target="fv-oracle"/>.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>comparison</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>How a consumer evaluates whether a deployed resource meets the fix threshold. See <xref target="fv-comparison"/>.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>auto_upgrade</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>When <tt>false</tt>, the provider does not automatically apply this version update. When <tt>false</tt>, <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>true</tt>.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>note</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>Human-readable clarification. <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14> when a fix arrives at different dates across release channels.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fv-comparison">
          <name>Comparison Values</name>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>gte</td><td>Deployed version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be greater than or equal to the specified value per the service's versioning scheme.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>exact</td><td>Deployed version <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> exactly match. Used for content-addressed identifiers (image digests, AMI IDs, OCIDs).</td></tr>
              <tr><td>date_gte</td><td>Resource's runtime build date or deployment date <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be on or after the specified <tt>build_date</tt>.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>channel_and_gte</td><td>Resource <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be subscribed to a qualifying release channel AND be at or above the specified version within that channel.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fv-aws">
          <name>AWS Version Types</name>
          <t>
            Defined <tt>version_type</tt> values for AWS services: <tt>runtime</tt>
            (Lambda and runtime-based services), <tt>engine_version</tt> (RDS,
            ElastiCache, Redshift), <tt>ami</tt> (EC2 and AMI-backed services),
            <tt>agent_version</tt> (SSM Agent, CodeDeploy Agent, ECS Agent),
            <tt>kubernetes_version</tt> (EKS), <tt>container_image</tt> (ECS tasks),
            <tt>managed_policy_version</tt> (AWS-managed IAM policies).
          </t>
          <t>
            For <tt>engine_version</tt>, the <tt>auto_upgrade</tt> field indicates
            whether RDS auto minor version upgrade is sufficient. When
            <tt>auto_upgrade</tt> is <tt>false</tt>, consumers must explicitly trigger
            the upgrade and <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt>
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>true</tt>.
          </t>
          <t>
            For <tt>container_image</tt>, <tt>image_digest</tt> (SHA256) is
            <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> over <tt>image_tag</tt>. When
            <tt>image_digest</tt> is present with <tt>comparison: exact</tt>, consumers
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> verify digest, not tag. Tags are mutable and
            <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be used as the sole verification method.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fv-azure">
          <name>Azure Version Types</name>
          <t>
            Defined <tt>version_type</tt> values for Azure services: <tt>api_version</tt>
            (ARM API operations), <tt>kubernetes_version</tt> (AKS clusters and node
            pools, with optional <tt>node_image_version</tt>), <tt>extension_version</tt>
            (VM Extensions), <tt>os_image_version</tt> (VM Scale Sets),
            <tt>runtime_version</tt> (App Service and Azure Functions).
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fv-gcp">
          <name>GCP Version Types</name>
          <t>
            Defined <tt>version_type</tt> values for GCP services:
            <tt>kubernetes_version</tt> (GKE, with <tt>release_channel</tt> field and
            <tt>channel_and_gte</tt> comparison for channel-gated fixes),
            <tt>database_version</tt> (Cloud SQL), <tt>runtime_version</tt> (Cloud
            Functions and Cloud Run, using <tt>date_gte</tt> comparison),
            <tt>image_family</tt> (Compute Engine public image families).
          </t>
          <t>
            For GKE, fix availability differs by release channel (RAPID, REGULAR,
            STABLE). The <tt>note</tt> field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enumerate
            channel-specific availability dates.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fv-cloudflare">
          <name>Cloudflare Version Types</name>
          <t>
            Cloudflare Workers does not expose a semantic version. Defined
            <tt>version_type</tt> values: <tt>runtime_build_date</tt> (Workers runtime,
            using <tt>date_gte</tt> comparison against <tt>build_date</tt>),
            <tt>deployment_id</tt> (Pages or Workers deployments where the fix requires
            consumer-controlled redeployment).
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="fv-oracle">
          <name>Oracle Version Types</name>
          <t>
            Defined <tt>version_type</tt> values for Oracle Cloud services:
            <tt>database_version</tt> (Autonomous Database, Base Database Service),
            <tt>kubernetes_version</tt> (OKE, with optional <tt>node_pool_image</tt>),
            <tt>image_ocid</tt> (Compute platform images, using <tt>date_gte</tt>
            comparison against <tt>build_date</tt>; OCID is region-specific so
            <tt>build_date</tt> is the normative threshold).
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-detections">
        <name>Detection Fields</name>
        <t>
          Detection fields enable consumers to deploy log queries, metric filters, and
          alerting rules that identify vulnerable configurations, active exploitation, or
          configuration drift. A record with <tt>vex_status</tt> of <tt>affected</tt> or
          <tt>fixed</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> include at least one detection entry.
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Field</th><th>Required</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>provider</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Cloud provider for this detection.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>service</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Log, event, or security service for which the query is written. See <xref target="detection-services"/>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>query_language</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Query language of the <tt>query</tt> string. See <xref target="detection-languages"/>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>query</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Detection query string. <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be syntactically valid for the declared <tt>query_language</tt>. Variable slots <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> appear where consumer-specific values must be substituted before deployment.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>detection_phase</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>See <xref target="detection-phase"/>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>description</td><td>REQUIRED</td><td>Explanation of what the query detects, why it is relevant, and any false positive caveats.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>pending_reason</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>When present, indicates this detection entry is a placeholder without a functional query. The <tt>query</tt> field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an empty string when <tt>pending_reason</tt> is set. See <xref target="detection-pending"/>.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>

        <section anchor="detection-services">
          <name>Detection Service Values</name>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Provider</th><th>Service values</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>aws</td><td>cloudwatch_logs_insights, cloudwatch_metric_filter, cloudtrail, security_hub, guardduty, config_rule</td></tr>
              <tr><td>azure</td><td>monitor_kql, sentinel_analytics, defender_alert</td></tr>
              <tr><td>gcp</td><td>cloud_logging, security_command_center, chronicle</td></tr>
              <tr><td>cloudflare</td><td>logpush, firewall_events</td></tr>
              <tr><td>oracle</td><td>oci_logging, cloud_guard</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="detection-languages">
          <name>Query Language Values</name>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Language</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>cwli</td><td>CloudWatch Logs Insights</td></tr>
              <tr><td>cloudwatch_filter</td><td>CloudWatch Metric Filter pattern syntax</td></tr>
              <tr><td>kql</td><td>Kusto Query Language (Azure Monitor and Sentinel)</td></tr>
              <tr><td>gcp_logging_filter</td><td>GCP Cloud Logging filter syntax</td></tr>
              <tr><td>oci_logging_query</td><td>OCI Logging query syntax</td></tr>
              <tr><td>lucene</td><td>Lucene query syntax (Cloudflare and SIEM integrations)</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
        </section>

        <section anchor="detection-phase">
          <name>Detection Phase</name>
          <t>
            The <tt>detection_phase</tt> field is normative. A consumer tool
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use this field to determine whether a detection is
            currently applicable and whether it should remain active after remediation.
          </t>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th><th>Retention Policy</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>pre_fix</td><td>Detects the vulnerable condition. <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> become misleading after remediation.</td><td>Deactivate or suppress after per-resource remediation is confirmed.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>exploitation</td><td>Detects active exploitation attempts regardless of fix status.</td><td><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> remain active permanently.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>post_fix</td><td>Detects exploitation attempts that remain possible after apparent remediation.</td><td>Activate at <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>; retain permanently.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>misconfiguration</td><td>Detects drift back to a vulnerable configuration after remediation. A confirmed match <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be treated as a window-reopening event.</td><td><bcp14>MUST</bcp14> remain active indefinitely after any <tt>opt_in</tt> or <tt>config_change</tt> remediation.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>
            A record with <tt>fix_propagation</tt> of <tt>opt_in</tt> or
            <tt>config_change</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include at least one
            <tt>misconfiguration</tt> detection entry.
          </t>
          <t>
            If a functional detection query cannot be authored at publication
            time, the producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> include a placeholder entry
            with <tt>detection_phase</tt> of <tt>misconfiguration</tt> and a
            <tt>pending_reason</tt> value from
            <xref target="detection-pending"/>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="detection-pending">
          <name>Pending Detection Reasons</name>
          <t>
            When a producer cannot author a functional detection query at
            publication time, the producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> still include a
            detection entry with <tt>detection_phase</tt> set to the required
            phase and <tt>pending_reason</tt> set to one of the following values.
            The <tt>query</tt> field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be an empty string. The
            <tt>description</tt> field <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> provide additional
            human-readable context explaining the gap.
          </t>
          <t>
            A producer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> publish an updated record with a
            functional query replacing the placeholder once the constraint is
            resolved.
          </t>
          <table>
            <thead>
              <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <tr><td>query_in_development</td><td>The detection query is being authored or tested and will be published in a future record update.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>awaiting_provider_telemetry</td><td>The cloud provider does not yet expose the log, event, or API data needed to detect this condition. Pending provider capability.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>no_detection_surface</td><td>No provider service currently offers telemetry sufficient to detect this misconfiguration programmatically. This value indicates a permanent or long-term gap.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>access_constraint</td><td>The record author lacks the provider environment access needed to develop and validate the query.</td></tr>
              <tr><td>pending_review</td><td>A candidate query exists but is under review (security, accuracy, or false-positive assessment) before publication.</td></tr>
            </tbody>
          </table>
          <t>
            A consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> deploy a detection entry that has
            <tt>pending_reason</tt> set. A consumer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> surface
            placeholder entries in operator-facing dashboards to indicate
            detection coverage gaps.
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-advisory">
        <name>Provider Advisory</name>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Field</th><th>Required</th><th>Description</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>advisory_id</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>Provider's own advisory identifier (e.g., <tt>ALAS2-2024-2456</tt>, <tt>MSRC-2024-0034</tt>, <tt>GCP-SA-2024-001</tt>).</td></tr>
            <tr><td>advisory_url</td><td>OPTIONAL</td><td>Direct URL to the provider's security advisory.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="schema-vex">
        <name>VEX Status</name>
        <t>
          The <tt>vex_status</tt> field aligns CRIT records with the OpenVEX (<xref target="OpenVEX"/>) / CSAF VEX (<xref target="CSAF-VEX"/>)
          vocabulary for composability with VEX-aware tooling.
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Value</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>affected</td><td>The resource type is affected. No fix is available, or fix has not been applied.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>not_affected</td><td>The resource type is not affected, or the vulnerability is not reachable in this deployment context.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>fixed</td><td>A provider fix is available and <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> is set.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>under_investigation</td><td>Provider has acknowledged the vulnerability but has not yet confirmed affected status.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t>
          A consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat <tt>vex_status</tt> as a record-level
          statement about provider fix availability, not as a per-resource remediation
          status. A record with <tt>vex_status = fixed</tt> and
          <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable = true</tt> represents the common
          real-world condition: a fix exists at the provider level, but existing
          deployed resources are not automatically remediated. Both facts are
          simultaneously true and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> both be surfaced to operators.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="provider-templates">
      <name>Provider Template Reference</name>

      <section anchor="pt-aws">
        <name>AWS ARN</name>
        <t>Canonical formats:</t>
        <figure>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
arn:aws:{service-prefix}:{region}:{account}:{resource-type}/{id}
arn:aws:{service-prefix}:{region}:{account}:{resource-type}:{id}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The <tt>{service-prefix}</tt> slot is always hardcoded (e.g., <tt>iam</tt>,
          <tt>s3</tt>, <tt>ec2</tt>, <tt>lambda</tt>, <tt>eks</tt>, <tt>rds</tt>).
        </t>
        <t>
          The <tt>{region}</tt> slot <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be hardcoded to
          <tt>us-east-1</tt> for globally-scoped services whose ARN schema
          requires the region field to carry a fixed value: <tt>iam</tt>,
          <tt>cloudfront</tt>, <tt>route53</tt>, <tt>waf</tt>, <tt>wafv2</tt>,
          <tt>shield</tt>, <tt>organizations</tt>, <tt>sts</tt>,
          <tt>globalaccelerator</tt>. For globally-scoped services whose ARN
          schema structurally omits the region field (the field is positionally
          present but the value is the empty string), the region slot
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be empty (<tt>{region=}</tt>). S3 buckets and
          objects are the principal example: the ARN format is
          <tt>arn:aws:s3:::{resource}</tt>. For all other AWS services the
          region slot <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a named variable or wildcard and
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be empty.
        </t>
        <t>
          The <tt>{account}</tt> slot is a named variable, except for resource
          types whose ARN schema structurally omits the account field (e.g., S3
          buckets and objects), in which case it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be empty
          (<tt>{account=}</tt>). The <tt>{resource-type}</tt> slot is hardcoded
          or empty per the service schema. The <tt>{resource-id}</tt> slot is a
          named variable or wildcard.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>AWS ARN Examples</name>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
arn:aws:iam:{region=us-east-1}:{account}:role/{resource-id}
arn:aws:s3:{region=}:{account=}:{resource-id}
arn:aws:ec2:{region}:{account}:instance/{resource-id}
arn:aws:lambda:{region}:{account}:function:{resource-id}
arn:aws:eks:{region}:{account}:cluster/{resource-id}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pt-azure">
        <name>Azure Resource ID</name>
        <t>Canonical format:</t>
        <figure>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
/subscriptions/{subscriptionId}/resourceGroups/{resourceGroup}
  /providers/{namespace}/{type}/{name}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <tt>{subscriptionId}</tt> and <tt>{name}</tt> are always named variables.
          <tt>{resourceGroup}</tt> is a named variable or wildcard.
          <tt>{namespace}</tt> and <tt>{type}</tt> are always hardcoded (e.g.,
          <tt>Microsoft.Compute/virtualMachines</tt>,
          <tt>Microsoft.ContainerService/managedClusters</tt>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pt-gcp">
        <name>GCP Resource Name</name>
        <t>Canonical format:</t>
        <figure>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
//{api}.googleapis.com/{collection-path}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <tt>{api}</tt> is always hardcoded (e.g., <tt>compute</tt>,
          <tt>container</tt>, <tt>sqladmin</tt>). <tt>{project}</tt> is always a named
          variable. <tt>{zone}</tt> is a named variable for zonal resources and empty
          (<tt>{zone=}</tt>) for global or regional resources.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pt-cloudflare">
        <name>Cloudflare Locator</name>
        <t>Canonical format:</t>
        <figure>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
com.cloudflare.api.account.{account_id}.{resource-type}.{id}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Cloudflare resources are globally scoped. There is no region component.
          A CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> add a region slot to a Cloudflare
          template. <tt>{resource-type}</tt> is always hardcoded (e.g., <tt>worker</tt>,
          <tt>r2_bucket</tt>, <tt>zone</tt>, <tt>d1_database</tt>).
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pt-oracle">
        <name>Oracle OCID</name>
        <t>Canonical formats:</t>
        <figure>
          <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
ocid1.{type}.{realm}.{region}..{unique-id}       (regional)
ocid1.{type}.{realm}...{unique-id}               (global)
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          <tt>{type}</tt> is always hardcoded. <tt>{realm}</tt> is hardcoded to
          <tt>oc1</tt> for commercial regions. Separate CRIT records
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be produced for government realms (<tt>oc2</tt>,
          <tt>oc3</tt>) when fix timelines differ. <tt>{region}</tt> is a named
          variable for regional resources and empty (<tt>{region=}</tt>) for global
          resources.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="pt-naming-conventions">
        <name>Parameter Naming Conventions</name>
        <t>
          Slot field names vary between providers by design. AWS ARNs use a
          consistent positional structure so slot names are uniform across
          services (<tt>region</tt>, <tt>account</tt>, <tt>resource-id</tt>).
          GCP, Azure, Oracle, and Cloudflare use service-specific path
          components (<tt>project</tt>, <tt>location</tt>,
          <tt>subscriptionId</tt>, <tt>resourceGroup</tt>, <tt>realm</tt>,
          <tt>account_id</tt>) because their resource path structures are
          service-specific. This asymmetry is intentional: CRIT adopts
          provider-native naming conventions rather than imposing a normalised
          abstraction. Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> expect different slot
          vocabularies per provider and <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> assume that
          all providers use the same field names.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="resolution">
      <name>Variable Resolution Rules</name>

      <section anchor="resolution-order">
        <name>Resolution Order</name>
        <t>
          A consumer resolving a CRIT template to a live identifier <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          apply substitutions in the following order:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>Replace all hardcoded slots (<tt>{field=literal}</tt>) with their literal value.</li>
          <li>Replace all empty slots (<tt>{field=}</tt>) with the empty string.</li>
          <li>Replace all named variable slots (<tt>{field}</tt>) with consumer-supplied concrete values.</li>
          <li>Wildcard slots (<tt>{field=*}</tt>) <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be resolved to a live identifier. For inventory enumeration, a consumer <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> enumerate known values to produce a set of resolved templates.</li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          After step 3, the resulting string <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid provider
          identifier conforming to the declared <tt>template_format</tt>. A consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate this and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> reject a template
          that fails validation after full substitution.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="resolution-fields">
        <name>Reserved Field Names</name>
        <t>
          The following field names carry defined semantics across all providers.
          A CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use these names where applicable and
          <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> reuse them for different semantics.
        </t>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Field Name</th><th>Semantics</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td>account</td><td>AWS account ID or equivalent top-level ownership identifier.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>subscriptionId</td><td>Azure subscription ID.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>project</td><td>GCP project ID.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>account_id</td><td>Cloudflare account ID.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>region</td><td>Provider geographic region identifier.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>zone</td><td>Provider availability zone or GCP zone identifier.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>location</td><td>GCP region or multi-region identifier as used in resource paths.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>resource-id</td><td>Unique identifier of the specific resource instance.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>name</td><td>Azure resource name.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>id</td><td>Cloudflare or Oracle resource identifier.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>unique-id</td><td>Oracle OCID unique identifier component.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>realm</td><td>Oracle OCID realm component.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>service-prefix</td><td>AWS service prefix as used in ARN construction.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>resource-type</td><td>Resource type component within an ARN.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>namespace</td><td>Azure resource provider namespace.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>type</td><td>Azure resource type or Oracle OCID type component.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>api</td><td>GCP API host prefix.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="exposure-window">
      <name>Exposure Window Computation</name>

      <section anchor="ew-definition">
        <name>Definition</name>
        <t>
          For package vulnerabilities, an exposure window can be approximated from
          version data alone: a package was exposed from the time the vulnerable version
          was released until the time the fixed version was installed. Cloud resources
          have no equivalent computation. There is no "installed version" to timestamp,
          no registry entry recording when a resource was last updated, and no version
          comparison that determines whether a specific running resource is currently in
          the affected range.
        </t>
        <t>
          The CRIT exposure window is therefore defined over time and consumer action,
          not over version ranges. A resource enters the window when it is deployed into
          a vulnerable configuration. It exits the window when a qualifying remediation
          event is recorded -- which may be long after <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> for
          resources where <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> is
          <tt>true</tt>, or never, for resources under <tt>no_fix_available</tt>
          propagation.
        </t>
        <t>
          Formally, the exposure window is the interval [W_start, W_end] where:
        </t>
        <ul>
          <li>W_start = <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date</tt> when present; otherwise
          <tt>vuln_published_date</tt>. When <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date_estimated</tt>
          is <tt>true</tt>, consumers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> indicate this in user-facing
          reporting.</li>
          <li>W_end is determined per <xref target="ew-wend"/>.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ew-wend">
        <name>Record-Level W_end</name>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr><th>Condition</th><th>W_end</th></tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr><td><tt>shared_responsibility = provider_only</tt> AND <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> is present</td><td>W_end = <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>. Window closed for all resources automatically. <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>false</tt>.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>shared_responsibility</tt> is <tt>customer_action_required</tt> or <tt>shared</tt></td><td>W_end undefined at record level. <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> opens remediation possibility but does not close the window. Per-resource closure requires a confirmed consumer action.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>shared_responsibility = customer_only</tt></td><td>W_end undefined. No <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>. Per-resource closure requires confirmed consumer remediation.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>fix_propagation = no_fix_available</tt></td><td>W_end = null. Window open. <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be absent.</td></tr>
            <tr><td><tt>provider_fix_date</tt> absent for any other reason</td><td>W_end = null. Window open.</td></tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ew-deployed-before-fix">
        <name>The Deployed-Before-Fix Problem</name>
        <t>
          When <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> is <tt>true</tt>, the
          exposure window for a specific resource instance is NOT closed by
          <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>. A consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> apply the following
          logic per resource:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <sourcecode type="pseudocode"><![CDATA[
if resource.deployed_date < provider_fix_date
  AND existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable == true
  AND no confirmed remediation action recorded for this resource:
    resource.exposure_window_end = null  // open
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          A consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> record a per-resource remediation event to
          close the window for that resource. A consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> mark a
          resource as remediated solely because <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> has passed.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ew-drift">
        <name>Opt-In and Config Change Drift</name>
        <t>
          When <tt>fix_propagation</tt> is <tt>opt_in</tt> or <tt>config_change</tt>,
          a remediation may be reversed by a subsequent configuration change, reopening
          the window. When a <tt>misconfiguration</tt>-phase detection fires for a
          resource, a consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> treat this as a window-reopening
          event. A consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> keep <tt>misconfiguration</tt>-phase
          detections active indefinitely for any resource remediated via <tt>opt_in</tt>
          or <tt>config_change</tt>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ew-rolling">
        <name>Rolling Replace Fleet Exposure</name>
        <t>
          When <tt>fix_propagation</tt> is <tt>rolling_replace</tt>, the exposure window
          is partially open during the fleet transition. A consumer <bcp14>MUST
          NOT</bcp14> consider the window closed until fleet replacement is confirmed
          at 100%.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ew-channel">
        <name>Channel-Gated Exposure</name>
        <t>
          When <tt>provider_fix_version.comparison</tt> is <tt>channel_and_gte</tt>,
          the effective fix availability date differs by release channel. A consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the channel-specific fix date derived from the
          <tt>note</tt> field when computing per-cluster exposure windows.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="conformance">
      <name>Conformance</name>

      <section anchor="conformance-producer">
        <name>Producer Conformance</name>
        <t>A conformant CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Emit records that validate against the schema defined in <xref target="schema"/>.</li>
          <li>Enforce the natural key uniqueness constraint: no two records in a corpus <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> share <tt>(vuln_id, provider, service, resource_type)</tt>.</li>
          <li>Apply slot state selection rules defined in <xref target="vs-selection"/>.</li>
          <li>Apply AWS region hardcoding rules defined in <xref target="pt-aws"/>.</li>
          <li>Set <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable = false</tt> only when <tt>fix_propagation = automatic</tt> AND <tt>shared_responsibility = provider_only</tt>.</li>
          <li>Set <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable = true</tt> when <tt>provider_fix_version.auto_upgrade</tt> is present and <tt>false</tt>.</li>
          <li>Set <tt>fix_propagation = no_fix_available</tt> and omit <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> when no fix exists.</li>
          <li>Include at least one <tt>remediation_actions</tt> entry for every record where <tt>vex_status</tt> is <tt>affected</tt> or <tt>fixed</tt>.</li>
          <li>Use ISO&nbsp;8601 <xref target="ISO8601"/> full-date format for all date fields.</li>
          <li>Include at least one <tt>misconfiguration</tt>-phase detection entry for records where <tt>fix_propagation</tt> is <tt>opt_in</tt> or <tt>config_change</tt>. A placeholder entry with <tt>pending_reason</tt> (<xref target="detection-pending"/>) satisfies this requirement.</li>
          <li>Compute <tt>vectorString</tt> as the canonical CRIT vector string from the record's own fields per <xref target="crit-vector-string"/>.</li>
          <li>Encode <tt>temporal.vuln_published_date</tt> as the PP metric value in Unix epoch seconds (UTC).</li>
          <li>Encode <tt>temporal.service_available_date</tt> as the SA metric value in Unix epoch seconds (UTC).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>A conformant CRIT producer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Include at least one detection entry for records where <tt>vex_status</tt> is <tt>affected</tt> or <tt>fixed</tt>.</li>
          <li>Populate <tt>provider_advisory</tt> when a provider security advisory exists.</li>
          <li>Populate <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date</tt> when determinable; set <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date_estimated = true</tt> when the date is an estimate.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="conformance-consumer">
        <name>Consumer Conformance</name>
        <t>A conformant CRIT consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Treat <tt>provider_fix_date</tt> as closing the exposure window only when <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> is <tt>false</tt>.</li>
          <li>Not substitute hardcoded slot values with alternative values.</li>
          <li>Not use wildcard templates as live provider API identifiers.</li>
          <li>Track per-resource remediation events separately from record-level <tt>vex_status</tt>.</li>
          <li>Treat a <tt>misconfiguration</tt>-phase detection match as a window-reopening event.</li>
          <li>Keep <tt>misconfiguration</tt>-phase detections active indefinitely once deployed.</li>
          <li>Use channel-specific fix dates for <tt>channel_and_gte</tt> version types when per-resource channel enrollment is known.</li>
          <li>Prefer <tt>image_digest</tt> over <tt>image_tag</tt> for <tt>container_image</tt> version comparison when both are present.</li>
          <li>Ignore unknown metric keys in a <tt>vectorString</tt> without error (forward compatibility per <xref target="vs-computation"/>).</li>
          <li>Reject a <tt>vectorString</tt> missing any registered metric.</li>
          <li>Not treat a <tt>vectorString</tt> as a complete record representation. Use the full JSON record for operational decisions requiring fields not carried in the vector (see <xref target="vs-information-scope"/>).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>A conformant CRIT consumer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>Present <tt>remediation_actions</tt> in declared sequence order.</li>
          <li>Substitute consumer-specific named variable values into detection query slots before deploying queries.</li>
          <li>Apply <tt>customer_deadline_date</tt> when computing remediation SLAs.</li>
          <li>Surface <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date_estimated = true</tt> in operator-facing exposure window reporting.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="upstream-integration">
      <name>Upstream Schema Integration</name>

      <section anchor="ui-strategy">
        <name>Integration Strategy and Phasing</name>
        <t>
          CRIT data is published via two upstream vulnerability schema ecosystems: the
          CVE List v5 ADP container and the OSV schema. Each integration follows a
          two-phase strategy.
        </t>
        <t>
          <strong>Phase 1 -- Extension (current):</strong> CRIT records are embedded as
          custom <tt>x_</tt> properties within conformant records of the target schema.
          This is immediately deployable without requiring changes to either upstream
          schema. Phase 1 records are fully schema-valid because both CVEListv5 and OSV
          permit additional properties with the <tt>x_</tt> prefix.
        </t>
        <t>
          <strong>Phase 2 -- Native integration (proposed):</strong> CRIT fields are
          expressed using native objects defined by the upstream schema wherever a
          semantic mapping exists. Fields without a native mapping continue to use
          <tt>x_crit_*</tt> prefixed properties within the appropriate extension points.
          Phase 2 requires coordination with CVEProject and OpenSSF but does not require
          either upstream schema to define new first-class fields for all CRIT concepts.
        </t>
        <t>
          A producer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> remove Phase 1 fields until: Phase 2 native
          fields have been published for at least one full release cycle of the target
          schema; the <tt>cloud:*</tt> ecosystem namespace has been formally registered
          with OSV schema maintainers or the ADP native field mapping accepted by the
          CVEProject schema working group; downstream consumers have confirmed migration
          to Phase 2; and a 90-day deprecation notice has been in the relevant records.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ui-cvelistv5">
        <name>CVE List v5 ADP Container Integration</name>
        <t>
          Vulnetix publishes CRIT data as an Authorized Data Publisher (ADP) in
          CVEListv5 records. The Vulnetix ADP container is identified by
          <tt>providerMetadata.shortName = "VVD"</tt> or by Vulnetix's
          <tt>orgId</tt> in the <tt>containers.adp[]</tt> array.
        </t>

        <section anchor="ui-cv5-phase1">
          <name>Phase 1 -- x_crit Extension (Current)</name>
          <t>
            In Phase 1 a single top-level <tt>x_crit</tt> field in the Vulnetix ADP
            container carries an array of CRIT records. The <tt>x_crit</tt> array
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> contain one entry per natural key tuple applicable to
            the CVE. The <tt>vuln_id</tt> within each entry <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> match
            the <tt>cveMetadata.cveId</tt> of the enclosing CVEListv5 record.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ui-cv5-phase2">
          <name>Phase 2 -- Native ADP Container (Proposed)</name>
          <t>
            In Phase 2, each CRIT record contributes one entry to the ADP
            <tt>affected[]</tt> array. Provider-native CVEListv5 fields carry data
            wherever a mapping exists; fields without a native mapping use
            <tt>x_crit_*</tt> extension properties on the <tt>affected[]</tt> item
            or at the ADP container level.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ui-cv5-mapping">
          <name>CVEListv5 Field Mapping</name>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt><tt>provider</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].vendor</tt> -- Provider key.</dd>
            <dt><tt>service</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].product</tt> -- Service key.</dd>
            <dt><tt>resource_type</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].modules[]</tt> -- Array of resource type strings.</dd>
            <dt><tt>template</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].platforms[]</tt> -- CRIT template strings as
            platform descriptors.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_fix_version</tt> (range bound):</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].versions[].lessThan</tt> and
            <tt>changes[].at</tt> -- Range [0, fix_version) expressed
            natively; full subschema in residual field
            <tt>x_crit_fix_version</tt>.</dd>
            <dt><tt>temporal.*_date</tt> fields:</dt>
            <dd>ADP container <tt>timeline[]</tt> array -- Each date as a timeline
            entry with a descriptive value string.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_advisory</tt> CVSS fields:</dt>
            <dd>ADP container <tt>metrics[]</tt> array -- <tt>cvssV3_1</tt> or
            <tt>cvssV4_0</tt> per the vector string prefix.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_advisory.advisory_url</tt>:</dt>
            <dd>ADP container <tt>references[]</tt> array with
            <tt>tags: ["vendor-advisory"]</tt>.</dd>
            <dt><tt>remediation_actions</tt> (non-compensating):</dt>
            <dd>ADP container <tt>solutions[]</tt> array -- One entry per action.</dd>
            <dt><tt>remediation_actions</tt> (compensating_control: true):</dt>
            <dd>ADP container <tt>workarounds[]</tt> array.</dd>
            <dt>Residual fields (no native CVEListv5 mapping):</dt>
            <dd><tt>vex_status</tt> -> <tt>x_crit_vex_status</tt>;
            <tt>fix_propagation</tt> -> <tt>x_crit_fix_propagation</tt>;
            <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> ->
            <tt>x_crit_existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt>;
            <tt>shared_responsibility</tt> ->
            <tt>x_crit_shared_responsibility</tt>;
            <tt>resource_lifecycle</tt> -> <tt>x_crit_resource_lifecycle</tt>;
            <tt>provider_fix_version</tt> (full subschema) ->
            <tt>x_crit_fix_version</tt>;
            <tt>template</tt> with slot syntax ->
            <tt>x_crit_template</tt> + <tt>x_crit_template_format</tt>;
            <tt>detections[]</tt> -> <tt>x_crit_detections</tt>.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>

      </section>

      <section anchor="ui-osv">
        <name>OSV Schema Integration</name>
        <t>
          Publishers may produce CRIT data in OSV schema format for consumption by OSV.dev
          and compatible tooling.
        </t>

        <section anchor="ui-osv-conventions">
          <name>Naming Conventions</name>
          <t>
            Cloud provider ecosystems are expressed as <tt>cloud:&lt;provider&gt;</tt>
            (e.g., <tt>cloud:aws</tt>, <tt>cloud:azure</tt>, <tt>cloud:gcp</tt>). This
            namespace is proposed for registration with the OSV schema ecosystem list.
            Until registered, tooling that does not recognise a <tt>cloud:*</tt>
            ecosystem <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> reject records using it.
          </t>
          <t>
            Package names use the convention <tt>&lt;service&gt;:&lt;resource_type&gt;</tt>
            (e.g., <tt>rds:db</tt>, <tt>aks:cluster</tt>, <tt>lambda:function</tt>).
          </t>
          <t>
            PURLs follow the form
            <tt>pkg:cloud/&lt;provider&gt;/&lt;service&gt;/&lt;resource_type&gt;</tt>
            (e.g., <tt>pkg:cloud/aws/rds/db</tt>). The <tt>cloud</tt> type is
            observed in the OSV ecosystem but is not a registered type in the
            <xref target="PURL">PURL specification</xref>. This specification
            acknowledges its use for OSV integration but does not define or
            govern the <tt>pkg:cloud/</tt> type itself.
          </t>
          <t>
            OSV record IDs follow the convention:
            <tt>OSV-&lt;year&gt;-&lt;ID&gt;</tt>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ui-osv-phase1">
          <name>Phase 1 -- database_specific Extension (Current)</name>
          <t>
            Each OSV record carries one <tt>affected[]</tt> entry per CRIT natural key
            tuple. The full CRIT record is embedded in
            <tt>affected[].database_specific.x_crit</tt>. Multiple CRIT records for the
            same vulnerability are published as separate OSV records, each with a distinct ID and
            a single <tt>affected[]</tt> entry. The <tt>aliases</tt> array on all records
            includes the shared <tt>vuln_id</tt>.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ui-osv-mapping">
          <name>OSV Field Mapping</name>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt><tt>provider</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].package.ecosystem</tt> --
            <tt>"cloud:&lt;provider&gt;"</tt>
            (e.g., <tt>"cloud:aws"</tt>).</dd>
            <dt><tt>service</tt> + <tt>resource_type</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].package.name</tt> --
            <tt>"&lt;service&gt;:&lt;resource_type&gt;"</tt>
            (e.g., <tt>"rds:db"</tt>).</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider</tt> + <tt>service</tt> + <tt>resource_type</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].package.purl</tt> --
            <tt>"pkg:cloud/&lt;provider&gt;/&lt;service&gt;/&lt;resource_type&gt;"</tt>.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_fix_version</tt> (range bound):</dt>
            <dd><tt>affected[].ranges[].events</tt> -- <tt>introduced</tt>
            and <tt>fixed</tt> events.</dd>
            <dt><tt>temporal.vuln_published_date</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>published</tt> -- RFC3339 format.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_fix_date</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>modified</tt> -- Set to the most recent significant
            update date.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_advisory.provider_cvss_vector</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>severity[]</tt> with <tt>type: "CVSS_V3"</tt> or
            <tt>"CVSS_V4"</tt>.</dd>
            <dt><tt>provider_advisory.advisory_url</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>references[]</tt> with <tt>type: "ADVISORY"</tt>.</dd>
            <dt><tt>vuln_id</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>aliases[]</tt>.</dd>
            <dt>Residual fields in <tt>ecosystem_specific</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>fix_propagation</tt> ->
            <tt>x_crit_fix_propagation</tt>;
            <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt> ->
            <tt>x_crit_existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt>;
            all <tt>temporal</tt> fields ->
            <tt>x_crit_temporal</tt>;
            <tt>detections[]</tt> -> <tt>x_crit_detections</tt>;
            <tt>remediation_actions[]</tt> ->
            <tt>x_crit_remediation_actions</tt>;
            <tt>vex_status</tt> -> <tt>x_crit_vex_status</tt>.</dd>
            <dt>Residual fields in <tt>database_specific</tt>:</dt>
            <dd><tt>provider_advisory.advisory_id</tt> ->
            <tt>x_crit_provider_advisory_id</tt>.</dd>
          </dl>
        </section>

      </section>

    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        This document has no IANA actions. Future revisions targeting standards track
        may request registration of the <tt>cloud</tt> PURL type with the PURL
        specification maintainers, and registration of the <tt>cloud:*</tt> ecosystem
        namespace with the OSV schema maintainers.
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>

      <section anchor="sec-detection">
        <name>Detection Query Sensitivity</name>
        <t>
          Detection strings specify exact log filter patterns for identifying vulnerable
          configurations and exploitation. A corpus of CRIT detection entries reveals
          what a consumer is and is not monitoring for. CRIT records
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be treated as security-sensitive and access-controlled
          in consumer systems.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-window">
        <name>Exposure Window Date Sensitivity</name>
        <t>
          The combination of <tt>vulnerability_introduced_date</tt>,
          <tt>provider_fix_date</tt>, and <tt>existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable</tt>
          can allow an adversary to infer whether specific consumer resources remain
          vulnerable. Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> expose exposure window details
          in public-facing interfaces.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-compensating">
        <name>Compensating Control Disclosure</name>
        <t>
          Remediation actions with <tt>compensating_control = true</tt> reveal which
          mitigating controls are in place. Consumers <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> expose
          active compensating control details in contexts where that information assists
          an adversary in targeting unmitigated surface.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-wildcard">
        <name>Template Wildcard Enumeration</name>
        <t>
          Wildcard templates reveal the structural scope of a consumer's cloud footprint.
          A consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> expose unresolved wildcard templates in
          contexts where asset enumeration is harmful.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-version-trust">
        <name>Provider Fix Version Trust</name>
        <t>
          <tt>provider_fix_version</tt> values are advisory in nature. A consumer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> independently verify that a deployed resource meets the
          version threshold. Container image tags are mutable; digest comparison
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be preferred. A consumer <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> assume
          remediation solely on the basis of a version string match.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-collision">
        <name>Natural Key Collision</name>
        <t>
          A producer accepting CRIT records from multiple upstream sources
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> enforce natural key uniqueness before serving records.
          Duplicate natural keys with conflicting field values can cause consumers to
          make incorrect remediation decisions. Producers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> define
          and expose a conflict resolution policy.
        </t>
      </section>

    </section>


    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <!-- Section 12: CRIT Dictionary                                  -->
    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="dictionary">
      <name>CRIT Dictionary</name>

      <section anchor="dictionary-definition">
        <name>Definition</name>
        <t>
          A CRIT Dictionary is a machine-readable catalogue of entries that
          enumerate the valid combinations of <tt>provider</tt>,
          <tt>service</tt>, and <tt>resource_type</tt> values recognised by
          this specification, together with the provider-native identifier
          template and supporting metadata for each combination.  A dictionary
          entry is the atomic unit of service coverage: it asserts that a given
          cloud provider service and resource type is within CRIT scope and
          provides the template and slot semantics required to locate instances
          of that resource type in a consumer&#8217;s inventory.
        </t>
        <t>
          A CRIT Dictionary is not a vulnerability database and does not
          contain vulnerability-specific data.  It is a stable reference layer
          that producers and consumers use to validate and resolve CRIT records.
          A CRIT record&#8217;s <tt>(provider, service, resource_type)</tt>
          tuple <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> resolve to an entry in a conformant
          dictionary before the record is considered valid.
        </t>
        <t>Two categories of dictionary exist:</t>
        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt>Spec Default Dictionary:</dt>
          <dd>
            The normative dictionary published alongside this specification
            in the specification repository.  It covers the providers
            described in <xref target="dictionary-providers"/> and
            representative service and resource type combinations for each.
            Producers and consumers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support the Spec
            Default Dictionary as a baseline.
          </dd>
          <dt>Extended Dictionary:</dt>
          <dd>
            A superset of the Spec Default Dictionary produced by a Vulnetix
            deployment or third party.  Extended dictionaries
            <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> add entries for services or resource types not
            present in the Spec Default Dictionary, and <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> add
            entries for additional providers.  Extended dictionaries
            <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> remove or alter the semantics of entries
            present in the Spec Default Dictionary.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dictionary-entry">
        <name>Dictionary Entry Schema</name>
        <t>
          Each dictionary entry is a JSON object.  All fields except
          <tt>notes</tt> are <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>Dictionary Entry Structure</name>
          <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "provider":        "<enum: aws | azure | gcp | cloudflare | oracle
                            | salesforce | sap | servicenow>",
  "service":         "<string: normalised service key>",
  "resource_type":   "<string: resource type within service>",
  "template":        "<CRIT template string>",
  "template_format": "<enum: aws_arn | azure_resource_id | gcp_resource_name
                             | cloudflare_locator | oracle_ocid
                             | salesforce_url | sap_btp_url | sap_odata_url
                             | sap_sf_url | servicenow_table_url>",
  "region_behavior": "<enum: regional | global-only>",
  "notes":           "<string: optional annotation>"
}
          ]]></sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
          <dt><tt>provider</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            The canonical provider key as defined in
            <xref target="schema-envelope"/>.
          </dd>
          <dt><tt>service</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            The normalised service key (lowercase, underscores).  This is the
            value used in the CRIT record <tt>service</tt> field and the second
            component of the natural key tuple.  Where a provider uses multiple
            common names for the same service, the dictionary carries the
            canonical key; synonyms are resolved to it by the producer prior to
            record emission.
          </dd>
          <dt><tt>resource_type</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            The resource type within the service.  This is the value used in
            the CRIT record <tt>resource_type</tt> field.  For services with
            multiple resource types, each type has its own dictionary entry
            with a distinct <tt>(provider, service, resource_type)</tt> natural
            key.
          </dd>
          <dt><tt>template</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            The CRIT template string for this entry, expressed using the slot
            syntax defined in <xref target="variable-system"/>.  After variable
            resolution, the string <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid provider
            identifier of the declared <tt>template_format</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt><tt>template_format</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            One of: <tt>aws_arn</tt>, <tt>azure_resource_id</tt>,
            <tt>gcp_resource_name</tt>, <tt>cloudflare_locator</tt>,
            <tt>oracle_ocid</tt>, <tt>salesforce_url</tt>,
            <tt>sap_btp_url</tt>, <tt>sap_odata_url</tt>,
            <tt>sap_sf_url</tt>, <tt>servicenow_table_url</tt>.
            The applicable value for each provider is defined in
            <xref target="dictionary-providers"/>.
          </dd>
          <dt><tt>region_behavior</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            One of: <tt>regional</tt> (the <tt>{region}</tt> slot is a named
            variable, consumer-supplied) or <tt>global-only</tt> (the region
            slot is hardcoded in the template; the resource type is not
            regional).
          </dd>
          <dt><tt>notes</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            Optional human-readable annotation.  Used to document aliasing,
            deprecation, or provider-specific constraints not expressible in
            other fields.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dictionary-conformance">
        <name>Dictionary Conformance</name>
        <t>A conformant CRIT producer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Validate each record&#8217;s <tt>(provider, service,
            resource_type)</tt> tuple against a conformant dictionary before
            emitting the record.
          </li>
          <li>
            Use the <tt>template</tt> and <tt>template_format</tt> values from
            the matching dictionary entry as the basis for the record&#8217;s
            template fields.
          </li>
          <li>
            Support the Spec Default Dictionary as a minimum baseline.  An
            extended dictionary <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used in addition but not
            in place of the Spec Default Dictionary.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <t>A conformant CRIT consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>:</t>
        <ul>
          <li>
            Reject records whose <tt>(provider, service, resource_type)</tt>
            tuple does not resolve to an entry in any dictionary the consumer
            supports, rather than silently ignoring them.
          </li>
          <li>
            Use the dictionary entry&#8217;s <tt>region_behavior</tt> field
            when constructing inventory queries from wildcard templates, to
            avoid submitting region-qualified identifiers for global-only
            resource types.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dictionary-versioning">
        <name>Dictionary Versioning</name>
        <t>
          The Spec Default Dictionary is versioned alongside the CRIT
          specification.  The dictionary version is the same as the
          semver string carried in the <tt>vectorString</tt> prefix of CRIT records.
          Additions of new entries within a minor version are backwards
          compatible.  Removal or semantic modification of existing entries
          requires a major version increment.
        </t>
        <t>
          Producers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> include a
          <tt>dictionary_version</tt> field in their extended dictionaries to
          allow consumers to detect stale dictionary coverage.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dictionary-governance">
        <name>Dictionary Governance</name>
        <t>
          The Spec Default Dictionary is maintained alongside this
          specification and represents the minimum baseline catalogue.
          It is not an exhaustive enumeration of all cloud resource
          types. Additions to the Spec Default Dictionary within a
          minor version are backwards compatible; removal or semantic
          modification of existing entries requires a major version
          increment.
        </t>
        <t>
          Extended Dictionaries are independently maintained by
          implementers and are subject to the conformance requirements
          of <xref target="dictionary-conformance"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          A conformant consumer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> validate CRIT
          records against a dictionary before accepting them. Validation
          requires a known, trusted dictionary as the source of truth
          for the <tt>(provider, service, resource_type)</tt> tuple
          space. A consumer that does not maintain a dictionary cannot
          distinguish a valid tuple from an arbitrary one; therefore,
          dictionary availability is a prerequisite for conformant
          consumption.
        </t>
        <t>
          A conformant producer <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> emit CRIT records
          without consulting a dictionary, but the resulting records are
          non-conformant until validated by a consumer that holds a
          dictionary containing matching entries. Producers
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> validate records against a dictionary
          before emission to avoid producing records that no conformant
          consumer will accept.
        </t>
        <t>
          Cloud providers are encouraged to contribute dictionary entries
          for their services. Community contributions are accepted via
          the specification repository. No IANA registry is proposed for
          dictionary entries. The dictionary is a template catalogue
          scoped by provider, not a shared identifier namespace;
          provider-scoped entries do not compete for a global name and
          therefore do not require a central allocation authority.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dictionary-providers">
        <name>Provider Identification Systems</name>
        <t>
          Each provider covered by this specification maintains a published,
          authoritative identification scheme for its resources.  CRIT
          dictionary entries do not define these schemes; they encode them as
          CRIT templates so that producers can emit identifiers that conform
          to the provider&#8217;s own published format.  Implementers adding
          dictionary entries for services not listed here <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          derive templates from the provider&#8217;s current documentation;
          those entries <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be contributed to the Spec Default
          Dictionary via the specification repository.
        </t>

        <section anchor="dictionary-aws">
          <name>Amazon Web Services (aws)</name>
          <t>
            AWS resources are identified by Amazon Resource Names (ARNs)
            <xref target="AWS-ARN"/>, a hierarchical URN-like format with
            the structure
            <tt>arn:partition:service:region:account-id:resource-type/resource-id</tt>.
            The ARN format is defined and maintained by Amazon Web Services;
            this specification does not alter or extend it.  The
            <tt>template_format</tt> value for all AWS entries is
            <tt>aws_arn</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>AWS CRIT template examples</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
arn:aws:ec2:{region}:{account}:instance/{resource-id}
arn:aws:iam:{region=us-east-1}:{account}:role/{resource-id}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The ARN service prefix matches the AWS service namespace
            documented in the IAM User Guide.  Globally-scoped services
            either hardcode the region component (e.g., <tt>us-east-1</tt>)
            or structurally omit it (e.g., S3 buckets), following the AWS
            ARN specification for that service.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-azure">
          <name>Microsoft Azure (azure)</name>
          <t>
            Azure resources are identified by Azure Resource IDs
            <xref target="Azure-ResourceID"/>, hierarchical paths within
            the Azure Resource Manager (ARM) namespace.  The path structure
            follows the pattern
            <tt>/subscriptions/{id}/resourceGroups/{rg}/providers/{Namespace}/{type}/{name}</tt>.
            The ARM provider namespace and resource type hierarchy are defined
            and maintained by Microsoft; this specification does not alter or
            extend them.  The <tt>template_format</tt> value for all Azure
            entries is <tt>azure_resource_id</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>Azure CRIT template example</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
/subscriptions/{subscriptionId}/resourceGroups/{resourceGroup}/providers/Microsoft.Compute/virtualMachines/{name}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The namespace segment follows the <tt>Microsoft.{ServiceArea}</tt>
            convention documented in the ARM provider list.  Resource path
            depth varies by resource type and is authoritative in the ARM
            REST API reference.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-gcp">
          <name>Google Cloud (gcp)</name>
          <t>
            GCP resources are identified by canonical resource names
            <xref target="GCP-ResourceName"/>, the full-resource-name form
            used by Cloud Asset Inventory.  The format prefixes the API
            service hostname with <tt>//</tt> followed by the resource path:
            <tt>//serviceName.googleapis.com/projects/{project}/...</tt>.
            The resource name structure is defined and maintained by Google;
            this specification does not alter or extend it.  The
            <tt>template_format</tt> value for all GCP entries is
            <tt>gcp_resource_name</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>GCP CRIT template examples</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
//compute.googleapis.com/projects/{project}/zones/{location}/instances/{resource-id}
//storage.googleapis.com/projects/{project}/buckets/{resource-id}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The API hostname prefix and resource path structure are published
            per-service in Google&#8217;s API documentation.  For inventory
            queries, <tt>{location}</tt> may be set to the wildcard value
            <tt>-</tt> to span all regions, as described in the Cloud Asset
            Inventory documentation.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-cloudflare">
          <name>Cloudflare (cloudflare)</name>
          <t>
            Cloudflare resources are identified using Cloudflare API locators
            <xref target="CF-API"/>, a structured dotted-string form scoped
            to a Cloudflare account.  All Cloudflare resources are globally
            scoped; the <tt>region_behavior</tt> for every Cloudflare entry
            is <tt>global-only</tt>.  The <tt>template_format</tt> value for
            all Cloudflare entries is <tt>cloudflare_locator</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>Cloudflare CRIT template example</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
com.cloudflare.api.account.{account_id}.zone.{id}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The resource type segment corresponds to the Cloudflare API
            object category as documented in the Cloudflare API reference.
            Zone-scoped resources share the same account-rooted prefix.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-oracle">
          <name>Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (oracle)</name>
          <t>
            OCI resources are identified by Oracle Cloud IDs (OCIDs)
            <xref target="OCI-OCID"/>, structured opaque identifiers with
            realm and region components.  Regional resources include the
            region segment; globally-scoped resources structurally omit both
            the region and availability domain segments, resulting in
            consecutive dots in the OCID.  The OCID format is defined and
            maintained by Oracle; this specification does not alter or extend
            it.  The <tt>template_format</tt> value for all OCI entries is
            <tt>oracle_ocid</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>OCI CRIT template examples</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
ocid1.instance.{realm=oc1}.{region}..{unique-id}
ocid1.compartment.{realm=oc1}...{unique-id}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The <tt>realm</tt> component identifies the OCI infrastructure
            partition; <tt>oc1</tt> is the commercial realm.  The
            dot-separated positional structure is authoritative in the OCI
            Resource Identifiers documentation.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-salesforce">
          <name>Salesforce Platform (salesforce)</name>
          <t>
            Salesforce resources are addressed by REST API resource URLs
            <xref target="SF-REST-API"/>, the canonical programmatic address
            for every sObject record in a Salesforce org.  Resources are
            org-scoped rather than region-scoped; the
            <tt>region_behavior</tt> for every Salesforce entry is
            <tt>global-only</tt>.  The <tt>template_format</tt> value for
            all Salesforce entries is <tt>salesforce_url</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>Salesforce CRIT template example</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
https://{instance}.salesforce.com/services/data/v{api-version}/sobjects/{object-type}/{record-id}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The instance subdomain identifies the Salesforce org.  The
            <tt>api-version</tt> slot follows the Salesforce seasonal release
            cadence (e.g., <tt>v61.0</tt>).  The sObject name in the path
            identifies the resource type and corresponds to the
            <tt>resource_type</tt> field in the dictionary entry.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-sap">
          <name>SAP Business Technology Platform (sap)</name>
          <t>
            SAP BTP resource URL conventions vary by product tier
            <xref target="SAP-BTP"/>: BTP core services use the BTP API
            endpoint form; ABAP Cloud systems use OData service paths; SAP
            SuccessFactors uses a dedicated API host pattern.  The
            authoritative URL form for each service is published by SAP in
            its API Hub and product documentation.  SAP does not publish a
            single unified resource identifier scheme; this specification
            encodes the per-tier URL patterns as CRIT templates without
            altering or extending the URL structures SAP defines.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>SAP CRIT template examples (one per product tier)</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
https://api.{region}.hana.ondemand.com/resourcemanager/v1/instances/{resource-id}
https://{host}/sap/opu/odata/sap/{service-path}/{object-id}
https://api{api-server}.sapsf.com/odata/v2/{entity-set}('{resource-id}')
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The product tier determines both the URL structure and the
            <tt>template_format</tt> value: <tt>sap_btp_url</tt> for BTP
            core services, <tt>sap_odata_url</tt> for ABAP Cloud and OData
            services, and <tt>sap_sf_url</tt> for SAP SuccessFactors.
            Implementers <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> consult the SAP API Hub entry
            for the specific SAP product to identify the canonical resource
            URL form before constructing dictionary entries.
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="dictionary-servicenow">
          <name>ServiceNow (servicenow)</name>
          <t>
            ServiceNow resources are addressed by Table API URLs
            <xref target="SN-TABLE-API"/>, the REST-addressable form of
            every Now Platform record.  Resources are instance-scoped with
            no regional sub-division; the <tt>region_behavior</tt> for every
            ServiceNow entry is <tt>global-only</tt>.  The
            <tt>template_format</tt> value for all ServiceNow entries is
            <tt>servicenow_table_url</tt>.
          </t>
          <figure>
            <name>ServiceNow CRIT template example</name>
            <sourcecode type="text"><![CDATA[
https://{instance}.service-now.com/api/now/table/{table-name}/{sys-id}
            ]]></sourcecode>
          </figure>
          <t>
            The <tt>table-name</tt> slot is the ServiceNow database table
            name (e.g., <tt>incident</tt>, <tt>sys_script_include</tt>).
            The <tt>sys-id</tt> slot is the 32-character hex unique
            identifier assigned to every Now Platform record, as documented
            in the ServiceNow Table API reference.
          </t>
        </section>

      </section>


    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references>
      <name>References</name>

      <references anchor="normative-refs">
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>

        <reference anchor="ISO8601">
          <front>
            <title>Date and time -- Representations for information interchange</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2019"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="8601"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="AWS-ARN" target="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/IAM/latest/UserGuide/reference-arns.html">
          <front>
            <title>Amazon Resource Names (ARNs)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Amazon Web Services</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="Azure-ResourceID" target="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/rest/api/resources/resources">
          <front>
            <title>Azure Resource Manager REST API Reference</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Microsoft</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="GCP-ResourceName" target="https://cloud.google.com/asset-inventory/docs/resource-name-format">
          <front>
            <title>Resource Name Format -- Cloud Asset Inventory</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Google Cloud</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="CF-API" target="https://developers.cloudflare.com/api/">
          <front>
            <title>Cloudflare API Reference</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Cloudflare</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OCI-OCID" target="https://docs.oracle.com/en-us/iaas/Content/General/Concepts/identifiers.htm">
          <front>
            <title>Resource Identifiers</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Oracle Cloud Infrastructure</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="SF-REST-API" target="https://developer.salesforce.com/docs/atlas.en-us.api_rest.meta/api_rest/">
          <front>
            <title>Salesforce REST API Developer Guide</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Salesforce</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="SAP-BTP" target="https://help.sap.com/docs/btp/sap-business-technology-platform/btp-api-overview">
          <front>
            <title>SAP Business Technology Platform Documentation</title>
            <author>
              <organization>SAP SE</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="SN-TABLE-API" target="https://developer.servicenow.com/dev.do#!/reference/api/latest/rest/c_TableAPI">
          <front>
            <title>ServiceNow Table API Reference</title>
            <author>
              <organization>ServiceNow</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

      </references>

      <references anchor="informative-refs">
        <name>Informative References</name>

        <reference anchor="CVEListv5" target="https://github.com/CVEProject/cvelistV5">
          <front>
            <title>CVE List v5 -- CVE JSON 5.0 Schema</title>
            <author>
              <organization>MITRE Corporation</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OSV-Schema" target="https://ossf.github.io/osv-schema/">
          <front>
            <title>Open Source Vulnerability (OSV) Schema</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OpenSSF Vulnerability Disclosures Working Group</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="OpenVEX" target="https://github.com/openvex/spec">
          <front>
            <title>OpenVEX Specification</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OpenVEX</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2023"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="CSAF-VEX" target="https://docs.oasis-open.org/csaf/csaf/v2.0/csaf-v2.0.html">
          <front>
            <title>Common Security Advisory Framework (CSAF) Version 2.0</title>
            <author>
              <organization>OASIS Open</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2022"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="EPSS" target="https://www.first.org/epss/">
          <front>
            <title>Exploit Prediction Scoring System (EPSS)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Forum of Incident Response and Security Teams (FIRST)</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC6570">
          <front>
            <title>URI Template</title>
            <author initials="J." surname="Gregorio" fullname="J. Gregorio"/>
            <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Hadley" fullname="M. Hadley"/>
            <author initials="M." surname="Nottingham" fullname="M. Nottingham"/>
            <author initials="D." surname="Orchard" fullname="D. Orchard"/>
            <date year="2012" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="6570"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="PURL" target="https://github.com/package-url/purl-spec">
          <front>
            <title>Package URL (PURL) Specification</title>
            <author>
              <organization>package-url</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2024"/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="CPE23" target="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/Legacy/IR/nistir7695.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Common Platform Enumeration: Naming Specification Version 2.3</title>
            <author initials="B." surname="Cheikes">
              <organization>NIST</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="D." surname="Waltermire">
              <organization>NIST</organization>
            </author>
            <author initials="K." surname="Scarfone">
              <organization>NIST</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2011" month="August"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="NISTIR" value="7695"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="RFC5234">
          <front>
            <title>Augmented BNF for Syntax Specifications: ABNF</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="Crocker" fullname="D. Crocker"/>
            <author initials="P." surname="Overell" fullname="P. Overell"/>
            <date year="2008" month="January"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5234"/>
          <seriesInfo name="STD" value="68"/>
        </reference>

      </references>

    </references>

    <!-- ============================================================ -->
    <section anchor="appendix-example">
      <name>Complete CRIT Record Example -- AWS RDS MySQL (Informative)</name>
      <t>
        The following is a complete CRIT record for a MySQL vulnerability affecting
        AWS RDS, illustrating the engine_version subschema with opt-in auto-upgrade and
        the deployed-before-fix problem.
      </t>
      <figure>
        <name>AWS RDS MySQL CRIT Record</name>
        <sourcecode type="json"><![CDATA[
{
  "vectorString": "CRITv0.2.0/CP:AW/VS:FX/FP:RR/SR:CA/RL:SC/EV:T/PP:1719792000/SA:1514764800#CVE-2024-6387:ec2:instance",
  "vuln_id": "CVE-2024-20967",
  "provider": "aws",
  "service": "rds",
  "resource_type": "db",
  "resource_lifecycle": "stateful_managed",
  "shared_responsibility": "customer_action_required",
  "vex_status": "fixed",
  "template": "arn:aws:rds:{region}:{account}:db:{resource-id}",
  "template_format": "aws_arn",
  "temporal": {
    "service_available_date": "2013-09-18",
    "vulnerability_introduced_date": "2023-01-01",
    "vulnerability_introduced_date_estimated":
      true,
    "vuln_published_date": "2024-01-16",
    "provider_acknowledged_date": "2024-01-20",
    "provider_fix_date": "2024-02-15",
    "customer_deadline_date": "2024-04-15",
    "customer_deadline_source": "internal_policy"
  },
  "fix_propagation": "version_update",
  "existing_deployments_remain_vulnerable":
    true,
  "provider_fix_version": {
    "version_type": "engine_version",
    "comparison": "gte",
    "engine": "mysql",
    "version": "8.0.36",
    "auto_upgrade": false,
    "note": "auto_minor_version_upgrade must be enabled
      for automatic application."
  },
  "remediation_actions": [
    {
      "sequence": 1,
      "type": "version_update",
      "title": "Upgrade RDS MySQL engine to 8.0.36
        or later",
      "description": "aws rds modify-db-instance \
  --db-instance-identifier {resource-id} \
  --engine-version 8.0.36 --apply-immediately",
      "provider_guidance_url":
        "https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonRDS/
        latest/UserGuide/USER_UpgradeDBInstance.MySQL.html",
      "auto_remediable": true,
      "requires_downtime": true,
      "stateful_impact": "backup_recommended",
      "estimated_downtime_range_seconds": { "min": 60, "max": 600 },
      "compensating_control": false
    }
  ],
  "detections": [
    {
      "provider": "aws",
      "service": "config_rule",
      "query_language": "cloudwatch_filter",
      "query": "{ ($.eventName = ModifyDBInstance) &&
        ($.requestParameters.engineVersion < \"8.0.36\") }",
      "detection_phase": "misconfiguration",
      "description": "Detects when an RDS instance is modified to
        a MySQL version below the fix threshold."
    }
  ],
  "provider_advisory": {
    "advisory_id": "ALAS2-2024-2489",
    "advisory_url": "https://alas.aws.amazon.com/AL2/ALAS-2024.html"
  }
}
        ]]></sourcecode>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="appendix-issues">
      <name>Open Issues (Informative)</name>
      <t>
        The following issues require design decisions prior to a stable v1.0 release:
      </t>
      <ol>
        <li><strong>vulnerability_introduced_date sourcing:</strong> What is the authoritative source? NVD, provider advisory, Git commit history, or producer-derived analysis? A structured date_provenance field may be warranted.</li>
        <li><strong>Detection query versioning:</strong> Cloud provider query languages and log schemas evolve. A query_language_version field on detection entries would allow consumers to detect stale queries.</li>
        <li><strong>rolling_replace fleet progress tracking:</strong> A structured fleet_remediation_event object may be needed for cross-consumer interoperability.</li>
        <li><strong>Oracle realm handling:</strong> Government OCI realms (oc2, oc3) may have different fix availability timelines. Confirm whether realm_overrides array within a single record is preferable to separate records.</li>
        <li><strong>CVSS version discrimination:</strong> A cvss_version discriminator on provider_advisory would allow consumers to apply version-appropriate scoring logic.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t>
        The author thanks the Wiz security research team for open-sourcing their cloud
        vulnerability database work, the Anchore team for open-sourcing their CVE
        enrichment work, the CVEProject and OpenSSF communities for the ADP container
        and OSV schema mechanisms that make upstream integration possible, and the OWASP
        community for providing a home for applied security standards work.
      </t>
    </section>

  </back>

</rfc>
        